<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable warning to such who profess themselves members of reformed churches, into what forme soever gathered ...</title>
            <author>Bayley, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1473B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12046771</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12046771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53099</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53099)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 857:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable warning to such who profess themselves members of reformed churches, into what forme soever gathered ...</title>
                  <author>Bayley, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page quote signed: Charles Baily.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53099:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53099:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Seaſonable Warning To ſuch who profeſs themſelves MEMBERS OF Reformed Churches, INTO What Forme ſoever gathered, or where-ever ſcattered over the face of the whole earth, but moſt eſpecially to <hi>France,</hi> and the parts adjacent.</p>
            <p>With a few remarkable QUERIES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Given forth in love to all ſouls, a tender viſitation of breathing deſires of good to the whole Creation, by a friend thereof. CHARLES BAILY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53099:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>try your ſpirits, and there is no difference between you and thoſe you ſeem to deny, for in nature ye are one, in pride and hypocriſie, envy, malice, and cruelty, drunkenneſs, ſwearing, lying, whoredom, deceit, and whatſoever is evill; and were the power in your hands, ye would be more cruel then thoſe ye ſeem to complain of, and in the ground there is no difference between you, for ye have loſt your ſuffering ſpirit, which was once amongſt you at the firſt, and are grown as vaine in your Imaginations as any of the heathen of the Nations? Therefore repent, repent ye alſo, and think not in your hearts that it will ſerve your turns, to ſay you are reformed, while iniquity and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is in your inward parts, and are not at all reformed from that (to wit) iniquity; though ye ſay ye are ſaved by faith in Chriſt, ye are found wholly out of that ſpirit and doctrine, which leadeth <hi>To do unto all men as ye would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould do unto you</hi> (as your fruits hath proved) ſome of you caſting out of the Synagogues or Temples, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, and as is foretold ſhould be done unto my ſervants: Therefore be ye warned in time, and remember how the <hi>Jews</hi> came under the reproofe of the Juſt, when they ſaid they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, whileſt they were <hi>Of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Devil, whoſe works they did;</hi> and do you not think but your evill deeds are as abommable—as theirs? they boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as well as you they were the children of my Covenant, while you and them trample the Blood thereof under your feet; for which cauſe a curſe came upon them, and ſhall alſo come upon you, if ye repent not, and take not warning in time, while my hand is ſtretched out towards you for good, that ye may live, and not die in your ſins, for if you die in your ſins, <hi>Where I go ye cannot come,</hi> ſaith Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the world, who is the Covenant of God given for Salvation unto the ends of the earth and untill ye come to this Light, ye are far from being children of the Covenant, as ye pretend, but in Covenant with Hell, Death, and the Devill, pleading for ſin as long as you live, which is the Devils Kingdom; and for ſo doing ye give men great ſums of money yearly, which is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53099:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> thing to the Lord God Almighty. And then you ſay you are Chriſtians by Baptiſme and the like, ſprinkling a little water upon the face or head of a child, and thereby have an entrance into the Church, and yet will not admit the ſame to the Roman-Catholicke, though their Water hath as much vertue as yours, and the child of the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth as much as the other, and both when they grow up are in one nature; which ſheweth plainly you are ignorant of the one onely true Baptiſme, which waſheth away ſin and corruption, and gives a true entrance into the Church which is in God, the ground and Pillar of truth, into which no unclean thing can have an entrance, for it is a ſpiritual Houſe, built with living Stones, elect and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus being the chief corner ſtone;</hi> who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it, <hi>That he might preſent it to God without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing;</hi> And this is the true Church and Baptiſm which gives an entrance into it, and the true ſaith which once came and takes the poſſeſſion. So read and try, and prove your ſelves, <hi>If Chriſt be not in you, ye are reprobates,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe what you will; and if Chriſt were in you, <hi>The body would be dead becauſe of ſin, but the ſpirit is life becauſe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> but how far you are from this, let the Light of Chriſt Judge in you; therefore repent that ye may find mercy, and think not that God will have reſpect unto your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, no more then he had reſpect to thoſe who ſaid <hi>They were Jewes and were not,</hi> for becauſe of that, he ſaid he would <hi>ſpue them out of his mouth;</hi> and ſeeing he ſpared not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural branches, but cut them off the root, becauſe of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, do you think he will ſpare you? Nay, verily <hi>The ſoul that ſinneth ſhall die,</hi> ſaith God; for he ſpared not the <hi>Angels who kept not their first eſtate, but hath reſerved them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the chaines of darkneſs untill the Judgement of the great day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let theſe things be a ſeaſonable warning unto you, for it was ſo, and is ſo, that he which is <hi>a Jew outwardly</hi> is not the true <hi>Jew,</hi> neither is he a Chriſtian who beareth the name outwardly, and hath not the nature of Chriſt; all ſuch are an abomination to the Lord. You are ſo far
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53099:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> from being leavened into his nature, which only maketh a Chriſtian, that if any one come amongſt you, and ſay he hath the Spirit of God, he is had in great deriſion amongſt you, and is laughed at, to ſcorne, though the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is none of his;</hi> and all who were Baptized with the true Baptiſme, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>So read, conſider, and try your ſelves, what ſtate you are in, and do not think that the nature of Chriſt is changed ſince the Apoſtles time, nay it is all one, though many have the name, and are out of the nature. You fall a quarelling and killing one another about their words; this was not the nature of Chriſtians, for they were the ſons of God, led by his pure Holy Spirit, which was <hi>Gentle, meeke, and eaſie to be intreated, full of long-ſuffering, and mercy,</hi> even to enemies, and ready to do good unto all; in which ſpirit walking, they did not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh, but in it conquered and had dominion over ſin, Hell, and the Devil; though a time of warfare they came to witneſs, before they came unto this ſtate, as all the Saints and holy men of God ever did; witneſs the travel of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the wilderneſs into the land of reſt, which is the true Type of all the travel of the faithfull; for they came to witneſs the true Baptiſme, as it is written, <hi>They were all Baptized into Moſes under the Cloud,</hi> who was a true Type of Chriſt, and becauſe of unbelief many did not enter, becauſe they received the falſe report, and believed they ſhould never o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome their enemies; which things relate all unto the true ſpiritual warfare of every true Chriſtian which did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and entered, and poſſeſſed the land of reſt, which is the true Sabbath; and it is written, <hi>He that believes hath entered into reſt,</hi> ceaſed from ſin, which is the enemy &amp; adverſary of all mankind; and to this did the true Chriſtians attain in this life, even a perfect Redemption from ſin, and did witneſs the Blood of Chriſt ſufficient to purge them from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; and ſaith the Apoſtle, he which hath <hi>Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh</hi> hath ceaſed from ſin, (Marke) ſuch ceaſed from ſin, and witneſſed the body of ſin put off; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53099:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> again the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith unto the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they were <hi>Servants unto ſin they were free from righteouſneſs,</hi> being then made free from ſin, they <hi>Became the ſervants of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> So theſe things did the true Chriſtians come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though you are not aſhamed to take their words to plead for the Devils Kingdome as long as you live, though the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>His ſervants ye are to whom ye obey;</hi> So he which obeys ſin, is a ſervant of ſin; and the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, let no man ſay <hi>When he is tempted, that he is tempted of God, for God tempteth not to evil, but when a man is tempted unto lust he is tempted of the Devil, and lust when it is conceived brings forth ſin, and ſin when it is finiſhed brings forth death;</hi> ſo be not deceived with vain words, <hi>For ſuch as you ſow, ſuch ſhall you reape; if you ſow to the Spirit, ye ſhall of the Spirit reape life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, but if to the fleſh, ye ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption; for the wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life.</hi> So come all to the gift of God, which is the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which he hath enlightened you withall, and you will come to know the free grace of God unto Salvation, which will teach you to deny all ungodly luſts, and not to plead for them, and to live <hi>Soberly and righteouſly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evil world;</hi> (Marke) this is the fruit and effect of the Grace of God, and is not onely given to talke of, and ſay you are ſaved by grace, while you turn from it in wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the Saints and Chriſtians did not, but came through the Croſs to be ſaved, even from ſin, and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from their vain converſation, which they lived in in times paſt, &amp; ſo witneſſed a new birth, which was of God, which ſinned not, being waſhed with water by the word, which word is Chriſt the Saviour of the ſoul; and all who comes to know the word abiding in them, they do know and witneſs this ſtate, even a perfect ſtate from ſin; and that was their boldneſs in the day of Judgement, that as Chriſt was, ſo were they in this preſent world, perfect, even as their Father which is in Heaven is perfect.</p>
            <p>So here is a true meaſuring line for you to meaſure your ſelves by, what ſtock and lineage ye are of, and who is your Father, and whom ye obey; for the true Chriſtians Chriſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53099:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> was their Example in all things, and left them a perfect Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that they ſhould follow his ſteps, who ſaid <hi>Learn of me, for I am meeke and lowly in heart;</hi> and the true Chriſtians followed him, and were like minded in all things.</p>
            <p>Friends, my hearts deſire is to the Lord for you, that you may be ſaved and come to the knowledge of truth, which truth will make you free from ſin and pollution, though this thing ſtumbled the <hi>Jews,</hi> when Chriſt ſpake it unto them, for they looked out at ſome worldly thing, not conſidering they were ſervants to ſin, which was the cauſe of all their miſery. Therefore be ye warned, and fear pleading for that which will be your utter deſtruction, if ye live and die in it; read through the whole Book of Scripture, and ſee if ever any Covenant of God ſtood with any Nation, or people, but as they did forſake their ſins; or, were there ever any people to whom God did ſo largely manifeſt himſelf as unto the <hi>Jews?</hi> and yet when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the holy Commandement, which was delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, did not the Lord forſake them? yea verily, and will all who do the like. But if any of you ſhall ſay, they were under a Covenant of workes, and we under grace; were they not under the Covenant of grace as well as any? yea verily, in all their travels did not the ſpiritual Rocke follow them, which was Chriſt? And after the Law was adminiſtred unto them by <hi>Moſes,</hi> did not he preach the true and living faith unto them? ſaying, they were not to ſay, <hi>Who ſhall aſcend or go beyond the Seas, that they may hear and do it;</hi> but what ſaid he? <hi>The word is nigh you, even in your mouth and in your heart, that ye may do it;</hi> and was not this the ſame word of faith the Apoſtle Preached, yea even the living faith, which gives dominion over ſin, Hell, Death, and the Grave, by which all the Saints of old had their glorious dominion, and by which the Juſt liveth; and they who come to witneſs this true and living faith, they know a Shield againſt all the fiery darts of the Devil, which faith <hi>Worketh by love,</hi> and love fulfilleth the whole law of God, which is to love God with all thy heart, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf. So here is the true faith, and the man which is in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53099:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> it does unto all men as he would all ſhould do unto him, which is the true Chriſtians life, and there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Oh! how doth my ſoul pitty you, to ſee the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance you are fallen into, though ye pretend the Scripture to be your rule, which condemns you in all your practiſes, as will plainly appear, when you come to be tried by them; doth any thing availe <hi>but a new Creature,</hi> doth not the Scripture ſay? and alſo doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>Except ye be converted and become as a little child, ye cannot inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Kingdome of Heaven?</hi> And againe, <hi>Except ye be born againe, ye cannot ſee the Kingdome of God?</hi> Is there any true Chriſtians but who witneſs this ſtate and birth? nay verily, there is not any but thoſe who followeth Chriſt through the Regeneration, who cometh to ſit with him in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdome; Is there any who do not ſuffer with him that ſhall Reigne with him? Conſider theſe things in the coole of the day, and do not any longer take up a reſt and a ſecurity in a beare name, but come to the nature, and then you will witneſs a true redemption out of all earthly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not plead for them, but loath them; for the Saints converſation was in Heaven, which are above you which plead for beggarly luſt, which ſhuts out of the Kingdome, <hi>For no uncleane thing can enter there.</hi> Theſe things I ſpeake unto you in great plainneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, as I am moved of the Lord, that ye may come to the true Salvation from ſin; for who knoweth Chriſt and his power, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to be in vertue as he is in name, even <hi>A Saviour of his people from their ſins;</hi> therefore is his name called Jeſus: God hath ſworne that he delighteth not in the death of a ſinner, for he hath prepared a way and a means for the Salvation of all that they might be ſaved; <hi>For he ſo loved the world, that he hath given his onely begotten Son into the world, that all through him might believe;</hi> for he is the Covenant of God, even a Covenant of Light unto all Nations, that he might be his Salvation unto the ends of the earth. This teſtimony <hi>John</hi> did bear of him, that <hi>he was the true Light which enlightens eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man which cometh into the world, and as many as receive him, and believe in his name,</hi> even in the Light, <hi>to them he giveth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53099:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> power to become the Sons of God,</hi> which is another birth then yours, <hi>Which is of the fleſh, and will of man.</hi> Read and conſider, you that deſire Salvation unto your ſouls, for it is the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods eternal love unto you, for I am truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by his pure Spirit hereunto, therefore whether you will hear or forbeare, I ſhall be a ſweet ſavour unto God, <hi>Even in them which believe, and in them which periſh:</hi> But my hearts deſire is that ye may come into the Covenant of God and be ſaved, even to be taught, led, and guided by him, for the way is plaine, and it is but one in all, even the Light which reproves for ſin, &amp; maketh manifeſt all the deeds of darkneſs though never ſo ſecret; for ſaith the Apoſtle, whatſoever makes manifeſt <hi>is Light:</hi> he that comes to that which makes manifeſt cometh to Chriſt, for ſaith he <hi>I am the Light of the world, I am the way, No man cometh to the Father, but by me;</hi> So come to the Light, and then you will come to the <hi>Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> &amp; this will be more then a bear name unto you, life &amp; truth, even truth in the inward part, which God onely accepteth, out of which all profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is vain; therefore he which comes to the Light, comes to the truth, and comes to know the teachings of God, as it is written <hi>All thy children ſhall be taught of me,</hi> and <hi>great ſhall be their peace;</hi> ſo in the Light you will witneſs the teachings of God, which is his holy Covenant with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>I will write my law in their hearts,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and put it in their inward parts;</hi> the law is Light, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and if you come to turn to the Light, you will witneſs the ſame. <hi>I will live in them, and walk in them,</hi> ſaith God; (Marke) this is the holy, true, and everlaſting Covenant of God to his people, and this the true Chriſtians came to witneſs, even their bodies to be the <hi>Temples of God</hi> through the Spirit; and God dwelleth with no unclean thing, neither dareth ſuch a one plead for ſin as long as he liveth, for they are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and made fit for their Maſters uſe, not having only the forme of Godlineſs, but the life and power, and they who had the form without the power, were to be turned from it; which power is the Light, which cometh from Chriſt and leadeth up to God; and the Saints were Saints in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53099:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Light, for they were ſanctified by it, which was the will of God: And as ſaith the Apoſtle, this is the will of God, even your Sanctification; this is no new Doctrin, but the good Old Way which God hath prepared, even for his <hi>Ranſomed ones</hi> to walk in, in which path, the way faring men (though fools) ſhall not erre therein, for the way is Light, as ſaith the Apoſtle, if ye live in the Light, and walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, then have, we <hi>Fellowſhip with God,</hi> and one with another; (Mark) fellowſhip with God, this Light leadeth unto, in which the Saints fellowſhip onely ſtood, which brought them to the knowledge of God; and he which ſaid he knew God, and walked in darkneſs was a liar, for the darkneſs comprehendeth not the Light, (which is the only habitation and Covenant of God) ſo as you come truely to confeſs your ſins, you will witneſs the Blood of Chriſt to cleanſe you from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; but if you ſay you have not ſin, before you come to this, and ſay it is done away in Chriſt, then you are lyars, and the truth is not you, no more then it is in them who ſay they have not ſinned; as you come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Blood of Chriſt, and its vertue, you will witneſs theſe ſayings to be true and faithfull, not onely to be tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of, but to be witneſſed in you, and untill you come here, you are perfect ſtrangers unto the ſeveral ſtates and growths the true Chriſtians came through in their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; there was little children, young men, and old men; for ſaith <hi>John, I write unto you, little children, that ye ſin not, and if any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world:</hi> (Marke) He free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered up himſelf for all; <hi>And by this we know that we know him, if we keep his Commandements: He that ſaith, I know him, and keepeth not his Commandements, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.</hi> (Marke) the true Chriſtians ſtate is life: And conſider what ſtate, and nature you are in, and whether ye keep Chriſts Commandement yea, or nay, for theſe things are of great weight and concernment unto you, even you that have taken up the name, but are out of the nature. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53099:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Whoſe keepeth his Word, in him verily in the love of God perfected: hereby know we that we are in him:</hi> (Marke) by this they (the true Chriſtians) knew that they were in Chriſt, becauſe they kept his word, and he which dwelleth in him <hi>ought to walke even as he walked;</hi> are you here? nay, your conſciences witneſſeth to your faces the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; therefore forbeare the name untill you witneſs the life, elſe the greater will be your condemnation; which is the Word of the Lord unto you all; therefore be ye warned in time. And againe ſaith he, <hi>A new Commandement I write unto you,</hi> which thing is true, in him, and in you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the darkneſs is paſt, and the true light now ſhineth: (Marke) againe they did witneſs the darkneſs paſt, and the true Light to ſhine, which Light giveth the Light of the knowledge of the glory of God <hi>in the face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which treaſure, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> we have in <hi>Earthen veſſels;</hi> this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, even the Light, they (the true Chriſtians) witneſſed in them, and walking in it, had fellowſhip with it, and one with another, <hi>For God is Light,</hi> and he which liveth and walketh in the Light, liveth and walketh with God, and witneſſeth a true tranſlation, as <hi>Enoch</hi> did, and is not ſeen, <hi>Becauſe his life is hid with Chriſt in God;</hi> and this is a true tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation from death to life, which is the true Chriſtians life, and he which ſaith he is in the Light, and hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a liar, and is in darkneſs even untill now; he which loveth his brother dwelleth in the Light, and ſtumbleth not: (Marke) he who loveth and walketh in the Light, ſtumbleth not, becauſe he walkes in that which maketh manifeſt all things, even the hidden workes of darkneſs, which by the Light is reproved and judged: But he which hates his brother walkes in darkneſs, and knoweth not whether he goeth, becauſe the darkneſs hath blinded his eyes; ſo he which walketh in darkneſs knoweth not whether he goeth, even becauſe he is from the Covenant of God, (which is Light) wherein he ſhould walke, as all the ranſomed and redeemed of the Lord doth: And this, <hi>David</hi> did witneſs, who ſaid, <hi>God is my Light, and my Salvation;</hi> and all which comes to the Light and lives in it, witneſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53099:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſame thing, and are not aſhamed to bring their deeds unto the Light, becauſe they are wrought in God; but he which doth evil, <hi>Hateth the Light, neither cometh he to the Light, becauſe his deeds are evil:</hi> Therefore come and try if your deeds are wrought in God, by bringing them to the Light; and if by the Light they are Juſtified, then none can condemne you; but if the Light condemn you, none can juſtifie you, <hi>For all Judgement is committed unto the Son, who is the Light, and inlightneth every one whith cometh into the world,</hi> which Light is <hi>a ſure word of Prophecy, whereunto if ye take heed, ye do well,</hi> (as the true Chriſtians did) <hi>as unto a light that ſhineth in a darke place, untill the day dawne, and the day Star ariſe in your hearts;</hi> for it is the light of the righteous, which lightneth more and more untill the perfect day, and gives a diſcovery of all things; but the wicked (being from that which makes manifeſt) walketh in darkneſs and knoweth not at what they ſtumble, which is a wofull ſtate, for they are from the light of the glorious Goſpel; and you to cover your ſelves, ſay the letter is (calling <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi>) the Goſpel, when you are ignorant of the Goſpel of Peace, which is Chriſt the true light and Saviour of the Soul.</p>
            <p>Therefore give care and harden not your hearts ye <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in this Nation, leaſt God ſmite you with a curſe, and leave you to periſh in your ſins for ever; therefore come all to the light, that a true regenerate ſtate ye may witneſs, as the true Chriſtians did, who witneſſed the ſtate of a child, a young man, and old man; and the Apoſtle writing unto ſuch, ſaid, <hi>I write unto you little children, becauſe ye have known the Father; I write unto you fathers, becauſe ye have known him which if from the beginning; I have written unto you young men, becauſe ye are ſtrong, and the word of God abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in you, and ye have overcome the wicked one.</hi> Read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the leaſt in this ſtate knew God, and as they did grow up in the knowledge of God, they came to overcome the Devil, who is the father of all ſin, which is a true Chriſtians warfare; therefore come away, <hi>And put on the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Light, and take unto you the Shield of Faith, and the fiery
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53099:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> darts of the Devil</hi> will come to be quenched by you; and as good Souldiers you will overcome, and witneſs the evil one overcome in you, which is the ſtrong man which keeps the houſe, but coming to Chriſt and witneſſing him, you will know the ſtronger come, which will take the poſſeſſion in you, and ſpoyle the ſtrong mans goods, who had firſt the Dominion and whole poſſeſſion in you. And this is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of life and truth unto you all, that ye may come to be true children of Gods everlaſting Covenant, and witneſs the anointing in you, which is the light, which will teach you all things, and is truth, and is no lie; and as the ſame teacheth you, if ye obey and follow it, ye ſhall abide in it, which will be your portion for ever, and is the true portion of all the redeemed of God, who come to witneſs the birth which is of God, <hi>Which ſinneth not, neither can they, becauſe the ſeed of God abideth in them,</hi> which ſeed is Chriſt the hope of their glory: And this is the myſtery which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, which was hid from Ages and Generations, which was then made manifeſt unto the true Chriſtians; and except ye come to witneſs this, ye are reprobates; for Chriſt Jeſus is that ſeed which was promiſed ſhould <hi>Bruiſe the Serpents head,</hi> which became head in man after tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and his head being bruiſed by the ſeed of the woman, came to be perfectly reſtored into the Image and glory he was firſt created in, even into the Image of his Creator, who is God bleſſed for ever more of all his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones, who witneſſeth this fulfilled in them, as many do at this day; Immortal &amp; endleſs praiſe be rendred to his holy name for ever, for they come to know that the power of the tempter is not of more force then the Redeemer; but the redeemed, even by Chriſt the Light, comes to know his head bruiſed in them, who ſeperated them from God; and this is the true and faithful Chriſtians ſtate and life, even to live and walke in the power of his Creator and Redeemer all the dayes of his ſojourning in the mid'ſt of a crooked and perverſe generation, in which pure righteous and holy life they cannot plead for ſin, but ſtands as living witneſſes againſt all unrighteouſneſs whatſoever; and for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53099:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> this cauſe are they hated and reviled, becauſe they are as a City which is ſet on a hill, that cannot be hid, and that torments the wicked; and they are the <hi>Salt of the earth,</hi> and have <hi>Salt in themſelves</hi> to ſavour and try all things withall, and are not afraid of being deceived, (but <hi>Tryeth all things, and holdeth fast that which is good</hi>) for they onely are the elect of God, and cannot (for it is impoſſible for them to) be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but on the contrary ſtands witneſſes againſt the deceiver and all his works, therefore are hated by his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, even as they hated Chriſt, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The world cannot hate you, but me it hateth, becauſe I teſtifie of it, that the works are evill;</hi> but the world loves its own, <hi>And the whole world lyeth in wickedneſs,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture: And who comes to be redeemed out of the world, comes to be hated by the children of the world, even as they did their Lord and Maſter; the ſervant is not greater then his Lord, who ſuffered the contradiction of ſinners, and laid down his life for his enemies, and prayed for them, which is the true Chriſtians life.</p>
            <p>So as you would prize your eternal happineſs, ſlight not this day, your day of viſitation, but prize it, and you will find mercy, for God of a truth hath much mercy in ſtore for you, if ye reject it not; but if you do, then tribulation and anguiſh ſhall poſſeſs your ſouls for evermore: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while you have a day and time prize it, before it be too late; and remember <hi>Eſau,</hi> who had a birthright and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and do you thereby take warning; and read, ſearch, and ſee your ſtate, if you are true Chriſtians and redeemed of God, and be no longer fed with a name, for they were a <hi>Royall Prieſthood, a holy nation,</hi> and did Reign as Kings upon the earth, even over the World, Sin, Hell, Death, and the Devil; and though on the earth, yet they loved not the world, neither the things of the world, but uſed all thoſe as though they uſed them not; being in the Light, which is Chriſt the wiſdome of God, they came to uſe all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the ſame wiſdome as they were created, and to the ſame end, for by Chriſt Jeſus (the eternal Word of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) were all things created; and as ye come to live and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53099:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> walke in him (who is the wiſdome of the Father) ye will come to the right uſe and underſtanding of all things, and know and witneſs the ends of the earth upon you, and your converſation will be in Heaven far above all created things: Therefore come all to the word by which all was created, even the good word of God, which is quick, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>and ſharper then any two edged Sword, dividing between the precious and the vile, the clean and the unclean, for it is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intents of the heart;</hi> and this is the true word which ſanctifies &amp; makes clean, which is Chriſt the Light, the Word of God, which will be a Light and a Lanthorn unto your path, if you diligently heed and follow it, as <hi>David</hi> did witneſs; and unleſs you come to witneſs this word in you, you can never witneſs Chriſt, nor the end of his coming, <hi>Who hath given himſelf for us, to redeem us from this preſent evil world,</hi> according to the will of God. Theſe things are plain to every ſingle eye, <hi>Who deſires not to hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> nor make <hi>Christ a cover for ſin, and uncleanneſs,</hi> by crying they are ſaved by Chriſt, and have remiſſion through his Death, and ſhed his Blood for their Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet witneſs nothing they are redeemed or ſaved from, and are aliens unto the Covenant of promiſe, which is <hi>That he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins;</hi> and his Blood which purifies, ſanctifies and makes clean, for ſo the true Chriſtians did witneſſe it, even through it they had acceſs to God, and were redeemed from their vaine lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations through and by it, even <hi>By the Bloud of the Lamb,</hi> which was offered up to God <hi>Without ſpot or blemiſh,</hi> who hath alſo given himſelf for his Church, that he might preſent it in like manner unto God, which is a ſpiritual building, <hi>Built and joyned together, a ſpiritual houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſacrifices acceptable to God, Chriſt being the chief corner ſtone,</hi> even he who the builders have in all Ages rejected and refuſed; therefore come to the living Stone, that ye may be joyned and united to it, as the Chriſtians were; and as you come to be joyned here, you will come to be one Spirit in the Lord, and be covered with it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which covering, wo unto you, as it is written, <hi>Wo be unto you
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53099:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> who are covered, and not with my Spirit,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) for the day is come and coming even upon you, <hi>O</hi> ye <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> as well as in all Nations, that all other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings will be too ſhort for to hide you, and will ſtand you in no ſtead in the day of tryall.</p>
            <p>Therefore be awakened, and awake, ariſe and ſtand up ye which ſleep in the duſt, and the Lord ſhall give you Light and underſtanding of the things which belongeth unto your peace, in this the day of your viſitation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſleep not any longer in a falſe ſecurity, leaſt they be hid from your eyes, &amp; you be left deſolate, and without excuſe for ever; for of a truth, this is the day of Gods everlaſting love and mercy unto you, which conſtraineth me to warn you, and wo would be unto me if I did not; but whether you hear or forbear, I ſhall be a ſweet ſavour unto God if ye periſh, therefore I uſe great plainneſs of ſpeech unto you, and not as mans wiſdome teacheth, but in the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit I ſpeak, beſeeching you to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled unto God, I being one who truly hath known the terrours of the Lord for ſin, and hath been accepted at the tribunal ſeat of God, for Chriſt ſake, in whom and through whom I have had acceſs unto God, and by his ſtripes am healed, and purged by his Blood from ſin and corruption, and this hath not been of works, but by grace I am ſaved, through faith in Chriſt, by which victory is obtained, through patience and hope, which purifies even as Chriſt is pure, <hi>Which hope is an Anchor unto the ſoul in the time of tryal:</hi> And this hath God done for my ſoul, not by any works of my own righteouſneſs, as though I had any thing to boaſt of above another, for all boaſting is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ever by the Law of Faith, neither have I any thing but what I have received of God, whoſe love hath been in an unexpreſſible manner extended unto me, ſince I gave up unto him, &amp; believed his report by his holy ſervants, &amp; meſſengers of his holy, new and everlaſting Covenant unto the ſons of men, which is Light; and in, and with the ſame love the Father hath loved me, am I drawn forth to invite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53099:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> you my Countrey-men after the fleſh, whom God mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me to viſit, even from a far Countrey, where my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward habitation was many years, even in <hi>Virginia;</hi> and truly my ſoul is often powred out unto God for you, and ſure I am if you do not wilfully reject his love, but open freely unto him, his love will touch many of your hearts, as it hath touched mine, which if you receive, you will I know with a ready heart and mind follow him, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all earthly treaſure to follow him in the delightfull way of peace, and holineſs. And dear Countrey-men, remember <hi>Moſes</hi> who choſe <hi>Rather to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, then to injoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, refuſing to be called the ſon of Pharaohs Daughter;</hi> and take all the holy Servants and Prophets of God for an example of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and ſuffering, through which, and by which they plainly declared, they ſought not a habitation in this world, but were ſtrangers and Pilgrims therein, <hi>Seeking a City whoſe builder and maker is God,</hi> into which my ſoul deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that ye may have an entrance and habitation, even into the new and Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem, which cometh down from God,</hi> into which nothing that workes abomination, or makes a lie can enter, <hi>Though the gates thereof ſtand open day and night, but without are Dogs, and Sorcerers, and all uncleanneſs:</hi> And this the true Chriſtians waited for, even for <hi>a new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and a new earth wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs;</hi> therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, Seeing theſe things, what manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought we to be?</hi> yea they were to be holy, juſt in all their converſation; for of a truth all the true Chriſtians came to witneſs this, even <hi>all old things to paſſe away, and all things to become new,</hi> without which the new creature cannot be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, <hi>Which is renewed after the Image of him who hath created him.</hi> Therefore as an Ambaſſador from God, I beſeech you in Chriſt, lay theſe things to heart, and count it not as a vaine thing, or as an idle tale, but remember that becauſe of ſin and iniquity, God did ever ſend Plagues and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto the ſons of men, and when they would not be warned thereby, he ſwept them away in his wrath, for ſo hath he appointed in his determined counſell, <hi>That the wicked
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53099:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall not go unpuniſhed,</hi> but they ſhall be caſt into Hell, and all who forget God, for he is no reſpecter of perſons, for <hi>of all Nations he who feareth him and worketh righteouſneſſe is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of him,</hi> but <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man which doth evil,</hi> for his wrath is revealed from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ungodlyneſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe of men, and he is not partiall in judgement (as ſome would make him) that he will puniſh one man for ſin, and not another, nay it is not ſo with him, for <hi>Such as every man ſoweth, ſuch ſhall he reap, and every one ſhall receive a juſt and due reward for the deeds done in the body, whether they be good, or whether they be evil:</hi> The unfaithfull ſervant had a Talent given him to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove as well as the reſt, but his unfaithfulneſſe was the cauſe that it was taken from him, and he caſt <hi>into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for ever,</hi> but <hi>the faithful entered into the joy of his Lord;</hi> and this will aſſuredly be the portion, and ſentence of all the ſons of men; the workers of iniquity ſhall be tormented with the Devil and his Angels for ever: And it will not ſuffice to ſay <hi>Lord, Lord, in thy name we have done many things,</hi> yea they came ſo far as <hi>to caſt out Devils, and propheſied in the name of Christ,</hi> (and ſo far as this, none of you at this day hardly ever came yet,) and notwithſtanding Chriſt ſaid <hi>he know them not, depart from me ye curſed workers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read and conſider, and lay it to heart, that ye may be an holy people, and come to anſwer Gods Everlaſting love which is tendered unto you, leaſt the grace of God beſtowed upon you be in vain, and looſe the entering into the Land of promiſe through unbelief, which was the cauſe why ſo many fell in the Wilderneſſe and dyed, though they were come forth out of the Land of darkneſſe, and had ſeen the wonders of the Lord, <hi>which are ſet forth as examples for thoſe who ſhould come after,</hi> for the Goſpel was preached unto them, as well as unto you: And truely from a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding doe I declare it unto you, that if ye be willing and obedient, a larger poſſeſſion never had any people then the Lord will poſſeſſe you with, <hi>and ye ſhalt eat the good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in peace;</hi> for if ye accept and embrace his love, and reject
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53099:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> not his counſell (which is freely tendered unto you) he will rebuke Princes and Kings for your ſakes; but if ye harden your necks, ye ſhall be of many people moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: And theſe are words of truth, and of a good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding unto you all, which will ſtand a witneſſe for God, either with you, or againſt you for ever, againſt you if ye reject it, and for you if ye receive it; for of a truth Gods Eternall and Everlaſting love is tendered unto you, in and through which if ye receive it, and be faithfull to what the Lord will yet further manifeſt unto you, ye ſhall be bleſſed with faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> for ever, who forſaked his Fathers houſe to follow the Lord he knew not whether, <hi>and ſtumbled not at the promiſe of the Lord,</hi> but was faithful, therefore was he called <hi>the friend of God, and the Father of the faithful:</hi> I ſay take him for an example, and God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will give you Dominion, and honour you before many, if you honour him; but if you deſpiſe him, he will deſpiſe you, and if ye refuſe to hear him now when he calls unto you, the day is nigh when ye ſhall call, and he will not hear, which is a word of eternall truth unto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ariſe in the Spirit of meekneſs, and ſtand a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuperſtitions and Idolatry, not onely in word, but in life and practiſe; and turn to the light of Chriſt Jeſus, which condemns ſin and evill in you, ſo will ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come children of the light, and become a living teſtimony againſt all ſin, ſo will ye be a ſweet ſavour unto the Lord in your generation, and happy will the man be who joynes to the Lord in deed and in truth in this work, his name ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance for evermore; ſo let the fear and dread of God Allmighty poſſeſſe your hearts, and the wicked ſhall be dreaded by you, and brought into ſubjection within you and without you for ever: And this is the word of the Lord unto you, and bleſſed will ye be if ye hear and obey it, for the youth ſhall faint, and the young Lyon ſhall ſuffer hunger, <hi>but they which feare the Lord ſhall never want any good thing,</hi> for the fear of the Lord is clean, and the beginning of a true Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore bleſſed is the man which feareth always, he ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53099:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> in his deed, and ſhall proſper and flouriſh like a green Bay tree, <hi>which is planted by the rivers of water, bringing forth fruit in due ſeaſon,</hi> to the praiſe and glory of his Creator, and the Lord will ſpread his table in the ſight of his enemies, while they ſuffer hunger: And this will the Lord doe for the upright in heart, whoſe hands are not polluted with blood, nor deceit harboured between his lips, even <hi>he ſhall ſee the travail of his ſoul and be ſatisfied,</hi> and his dayes ſhall be proſperous in the land of promiſe, and the ſons of the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens ſhall be his ſervants; this ſhall ſurely be the heritage of thoſe who confeſſe and forſake their ſins, but he which hideth it ſhall not proſper, even his prayers ſhall be loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto the Lord, and all his ſacrifices an abominable abomination; but he which purifieth his way <hi>by taking heed unto the Law of the Lord,</hi> though he be ſimple, yet ſhall he be made wiſe, and his ſoul ſhall be converted, for the Lord will perfect his glorious praiſe in the mouths of babes and ſucklings, and this thing ſhall be marvelous in the eyes of many.</p>
            <p>Theſe are propheſies of things which ſhall <hi>ſhortly come to paſſe;</hi> therefore bleſſed is he which watcheth, that he may not be found naked, for <hi>the day of the Lord is coming on like a theif in the night</hi> upon all the inhabitants of the Earth, wherein the hearts of all ſhall be made manifeſt, and made bare and naked, of what Nation or profeſſion ſoever, and it ſhall prove you who ſay <hi>you are Jews and are not,</hi> and every mans works ſhall be tryed of what ſort they are, and all coverings beſides the pure Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord ſhall be as <hi>Adams</hi> fig-Leaves were, and when the Lord ſhall call them to an account, they ſhall fear to appear before him becauſe of their tranſgreſſions, and Gods witneſſe in all ſhall anſwer unto his juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which ſhall come upon them, the hypocrites ſhall weep and howle, and <hi>many ſhall call to the Hills and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to hide them from the wrath of the Lamb,</hi> whom they have willfully deſpiſed and rejected: Therefore be ye warned in time, and ſee and ſearch diligently what you are built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for no other foundation ſhall be able to abide the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53099:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> day of Gods controverſie with the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men, but the Rock of ages, and he which is not built upon this, let him be never ſo ſecure in his own conceit or in the eye of fleſh, his building ſhall utterly periſh and come to nought, and great ſhall be his ruine: Therefore come all to the Light, and make no other foundation but that, if ye deſire to abide the day of tryal which is neer, even at the dore; therefore this warning is ſent unto you in an acceptable time, that ye may take warning before it be too late, for a conſummate decree is determined of the Lord, which ſhall conſume and deſtroy all the workers of iniquity for ever; therefore bleſſed will the man be who hath not walked in their way, <hi>nor ſitteth in the ſeat of the ſcornfull</hi> after he is warned, <hi>but ſhall cleave to the Law of God, and meditate therein,</hi> his off-ſpring ſhall be proſperous in the Earth, and his name ſhall be written in the book of life for ever, he ſhall waſh his garments white in the blood of the Lamb, and follow him, who hath a Bow and a Sword, and maketh war in righteouſneſs againſt the Dragon and his Followers, (even the Man of Sin) who hath long ſitten in the Temple of God, and ſaid, <hi>He is God,</hi> but by the Lamb ſhall he be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and his followers, and all that are found in reſiſtance of Gods power ſhall be caſt into the pit of endleſſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ever; and the day is already dawned wherein this glorious work ſhall be accompliſhed: Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware with whom ye joyn in battel, for the Lamb makes war in righteouſneſs againſt all ſin and the appearance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but the Dragon and his followers ſhal be to uphold it, and plead for it, and impriſon ſuch as bear teſtimony againſt it, ſo each will be known by their weapons, their fruits, and their colours; the one's weapons are ſpiritual, the others carnal; the one is in unrighteouſneſſe, the other in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the one is in blood and revenge, the other in ſuffering and patience, ſo you may eaſily diſtinguiſh between them, and will not be able to plead ignorance in the day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for it was ever ſo from the beginning, the juſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering by the unjuſt, the ſeed of the Bond-woman perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeed of the Free-woman, which never perſecuted
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53099:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> any; therefore be ye warned of joyning with the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpirit of Antichriſt, for if you doe, you ſhall aſſuredly as the Lord God of Heaven and Earth lives partake of his plagues; but rather caſt out the Bond-woman and her ſon, that ye may be heirs with the ſeed of the Free-woman which keep the Commandements of God, ſo will ye be <hi>heirs of the promiſe,</hi> and of the mercy of God, which is freely tendered unto you, through his ſimple ſervant, who is at preſent a ſufferer in the patience and tribulation of the Lamb, on whom the Lord hath laid a neceſſity to warn thee O nation of <hi>France,</hi> that thou mayſt find mercy in this the day of Gods free love, which is tendered unto thee; and though this reacheth unto the whole Nation, yet in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular it is ſent to you who are called by the name of the Reformed Religion, to the end that ye may not only be ſo in name, but alſo in life and practiſe, without which your name will but adde unto your condemnation, as hath already been told you: God is purpoſed to try you and your foundation, and a name will not ſerve the turn, and except ye partake of the nature of the ſufferance of Gods ſeed and ſpirit of truth in you, and turn to the Lord <hi>by putting away the evil of your doings,</hi> ye ſhall ſurely partake of her plagues; which is the word of the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth unto you all, for her ſins have exceeded the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the meaſure of her iniquity is even up, and judgment is already prepared for her; therefore be ye ſeperated from your iniquities in time, for the word is gone out of the mouth of the Lord, and can never be recalled, but ſhall ſurely accompliſh the thing which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; therefore my bowels are drawn forth in love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that ye may not periſh with the uncircumciſed and unclean, but that rather ye may come to repentance and amendment of life, and live for ever, which is the true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of his ſoul.</p>
            <p>Friends, the Lord is about to do a wonderful work in the Earth, which many cannot believe, though it were told them, but the upright in heart ſhall ſee it and praiſe him, yea the youth ſhall rejoyce, and the virgins ſhall be glad,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53099:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the Saints ſhall admire, and ſmite upon their breaſts in beholding the wonderful works of the Allmighty, which he purpoſeth to doe in this generation: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give ear unto me, and be not hard of heart nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing, and I will through the ſpirit of the Lord which is upon me, ſhew unto you the certainty of things which ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe. The Lord will caſt down the haughty and the proud from his throne, and will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt the humble and the meek, yea, <hi>he will rebuke the proud, and give grace unto the humble:</hi> He will exalt his horn over all that ſhall riſe up againſt him, he will break the bond of oppreſſion, and ſet the Nations at liberty, that his name may be glorified from one end of the Earth unto the other, though at preſent his name is not known amongſt the ſons of men, and he be more a ſtranger, and leſs known amongſt them, then the <hi>Ox to his owner, or the Aſs to his maſters crib,</hi> yet ſhall the knowledge of him cover the whole earth, even as the waters cover the Seas: He will overturn all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and all Idols for ever, and all who ſhall ſet a hand to uphold them; all Idol Prieſts ſhall be turned into confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ever; the haughty ſeat ſhall be laid low, and the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the meek ſhal be exalted, yea, he will by his own arm and Allmighty power ariſe, and plead the cauſe of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and ſet the oppreſſed free, and enlarg the borders of the innocent, and the meek ſhall take the poſſeſſion, and the glorious glory of his renown ſhall go over all, which ſhall ſtrike dread unto his enemies; he will threſh the mountaines to duſt before him, and the wicked ſhall be but as the ſtubble which is dried before the fire, and ſhall be conſumed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; he who is mightier then the mightieſt will doe this; he even <hi>he before whom all Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket, and weigheth the hills in a ſcale, and the mountains in a ballance, and meaſureth the waters in the hollow of his hand,</hi> will accompliſh the thing which he hath purpoſed, and the word which is gone out of his mouth; for as the rain which falleth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth and returneth not again, ſo is the word of the Lord <hi>which is gone out of his mouth, which ſhall not return,</hi> but ſhall accompliſh his purpoſe, which is to ſubdue all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53099:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Kingdomes of this World, into the ſubjection of his own only anointed ſeed, to live and reign over all, and in all, who is bleſſed for evermore, <hi>in whom all the promiſes of the father are Yea, and Amen,</hi> for <hi>the promiſe was not unto many, but unto the ſeed,</hi> when he ſpake unto <hi>Abraham the Father of the faithfull, In thy Seed ſhall all the Nations of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> which Seed is Chriſt which ſhall have the Dominion in all, and over all for ever: Let him which readeth underſtand; <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhall be put upon his ſhoulder,</hi> and who will not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubject unto it ſhall be beaten to pieces with his Iron Rod, with which he ſhall rule all Nations; <hi>and this is the little ſtone which is cut out of the mountain without hands, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great mountain, and covered the whole Earth,</hi> which haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth apace to be fulfilled, even ſo ſaith my Soul, Amen, and Amen. And for the fulfilling of this his glorious word, the Lord will not onely ſhake the Earth, but <hi>the Heavens alſo,</hi> and will Overturn, Overturn, Overturn Kings, Princes, and Powers, even all thoſe who ſhall riſe up againſt him, and will tear them in pieces, as he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready apparently done; when the Lord will work who ſhall lett? <hi>the Heathen may rage, and the people imagine a vain thing, and the Judges of the Earth may take counſell againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed,</hi> but all in vain, for he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt him to reign <hi>upon his holy hill of Sion</hi> for evermore, in the ſight of all his enemies, to their utter overthrow and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ever: <hi>Your Judges ſhall be reſtored as at the firſt, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers as at the beginning,</hi> who will not judg for gift, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the wicked ſhall no more be called good, nor the churle liberall, light ſhall not be put for darkneſſe, nor darkneſſe for light, but all ſhall be judged by him who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in ſecret, and who lives for ever, whoſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an everlaſting Dominion, of which there is no end.</p>
            <p>Therefore come to the juſt in you all in the particular, even to the Seed of God in you all, which of his infinite mercy he hath left in you, elſe long ere now had ye been deſtroyed, and made like unto <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> but for his ſeed ſake hath he withheld his hand from deſtroying you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53099:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> untill this day; and conſider the end of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof, and their end, when the juſt was taken from amongſt them, and even as it was with them, ſo ſhall it be with you; if you harden your hearts, and will not hear, the Lord will take the juſt Seed from you, which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth dayly by you, and is oppreſſed in you, even as a Cart which is preſſed and loaden with ſheaves, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as <hi>the juſt was in Sodom by their unrighteous and ungodly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation;</hi> and if it be once taken away from you, though the faithfull may make interceſſion for you, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did for them, yet as ſure as the Lord God of Heaven and Earth lives, your end ſhall be as theirs, for if once the juſt in you be taken away, nought but fury and vengeance will be poured upon you from Heaven, untill you be utterly ſwallowed up with the eternall flames of Gods fury and vengeance for evermore; for whoſe ſake I am now moved to warn you from the wrath which is to come, and if you refuſe and reject, and deſpiſe his everlaſting Meſſengers, (as they did,) take them for an example (for God hath made them ſo) of his wrath, to all who ſhall reject his loving kindneſſe, mercy and counſel.</p>
            <p>Therefore in bowels of mercy and pity am I drawn forth again, and again to warn you, and adviſe and beſeech you to turn unto the juſt pure holy principle of God in you, and give up to be guided by it, and governed by it in all things, that ye may be leavened into its own nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the incorruptible nature of God, that ye may come to witneſſe the new creature, which is the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>over which the ſecond Death hath no power, and as many of you as come to walk according to this rule, peace will be unto you</hi> and with you for ever, <hi>peace which the world can neither give</hi> nor take from you, even the peace of God, which will rule in your hearts, which will keep your hearts and minds ſpotleſſe and blameleſſe for ever; and the power of the croſſe of Chriſt you will come to witneſſe <hi>to be the power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> as you believe and are ſubject unto it, whereby the world will become crucified unto you, and you unto the world, and nothing elſe will you deſire to glory in, but will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53099:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> come even to be aſhamed of thoſe things which ye now delight in, and have no more pleaſure in them, nor faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelves as you did in the former time of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as the Heathen did in vain and fooliſh habit, idle and fooliſh talk, ſuch things will be an abomination unto the Lord of your life, by whom ye breath, and nothing can or will proceed out of your mouth but that which is good <hi>to the uſe of edifying,</hi> and according to the promiſe of God you will come to witneſſe, even <hi>the pouring out of his Spirit upon you, and your Sons, and your daughters ſhall prophecy, your young men ſhall ſee viſions, and your old men ſhall dream dreams; and every one of you ſhall ſit under his own Vine, and under his own Fig-tree, and none ſhall make you affraid;</hi> and you will not need to go to men for teaching, <hi>nor every one ſay to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour know the Lord, for all of you ſhall know him from the leaſt unto the greateſt, and ſhall ſay one to another, come let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, and he will teach us of his wayes,</hi> and we will walk in his light for ever; and the Lord will make a hedg about you, and ſet his holy Angels to watch over you, and prune you, that as ye come to bring forth fruit unto him, ye may bring it forth more abundantly; to the honour and delight of the Lord will ye be for ever, which his own right hand hath planted, and none ſhall be able to pluck you up, for he will keep you in the hollow of his hand, and they which ſhall touch you to harm you, ſhall be as though they touched the apple of his eye; and though for a time ſome of you may be ſuffered to be tryed for the tryal of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet aſſuredly, <hi>it ſhall be but for a ſhort ſeaſon,</hi> &amp; a book of remembrance thereof will be written before the Lord, and you will delight to meet often together to ſpeak of his goodneſs, and he will aſſuredly be in the mid'ſt of you, and ye ſhall be his Temple Sanctified and made meet for his Uſe, and he will delight to take up his habitation with you for ever; and remember Satan may have power given to kill ſome of you, and put ſome of you in priſon <hi>ten days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read and underſtand, and be not diſmayed at theſe things when they ſhall come upon you, <hi>For ſo did they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute of old the holy Prophets of God before you;</hi> and if any of you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53099:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall go in this cauſe to ſave your lives, ye ſhall aſſuredly loſe it, but they which ſhall lay it downe for this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall ſurely ſave it; <hi>And whoſoever ſhall forſake Father or Mother, for my ſake</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall receive in this life an hundred fold, and in the world to come life everlaſting.</hi> And as I have ſaid, a day and a time of tryal may come over you, <hi>But a ſhort worke will the Lord make in the earth</hi> for his Seeds ſake, <hi>And the Rod of the wicked ſhall not alwayes rest upon the back of the righteous, ſaith the Lord God Allmighty:</hi> But I have ſaid (in and through the good Spirit of the Lord, and by the ſtrength of his own Arm which is made bare) he will burſt the bonds of your oppreſſors aſunder, that his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſeed may go free, even to the ends of the uttermoſt habitations of the earth.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay again to the holy Seed in you, even the Seed of the Kingdome, <hi>Which is as a grain of muſtard ſeed,</hi> yea the leaſt of all things in you, which if ye diligently need, prize and follow, it will become a great plant, and cover the whole earth in you; which if ye do, the good which I have ſhewed you in faithfulneſſe to God, and which is to all your immortal ſouls, will come upon you; but if ye refuſe and reject the good councel of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and joyne to the power of the oppreſſor to keep the Seed in bondage, then know as ſure as the Lord liveth, the juſt ſhall be taken from you, and all the evil I have been made to Prophecy of ſhall come upon your heads in a day when ye looked not for it, even when ye may be eating and drinking, and Marrying and giving in marriage. Remember the old world, and take ye warning before it be too late, <hi>For the Spirit of the Lord will not alwayes ſtrive with man,</hi> which is the Word of the Lord God unto you all, and wo be unto that man, or Nation, as the Spirit of the Lord ſhall ceaſe ſtriving with, better were it that they had never been born; for a manifeſtation of his holy Spirit hath been given to <hi>every one to profit withall,</hi> which is the Lords money, and your talent, and miſery will be the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that hide their Maſters money in the earth (for ſuch have grieved his righteous Spirit) which will be too
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53099:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> heavy for them to bear in the end. Read the parable, and againe I ſay be ye warned, and while ye have time prize it before it be too late. Remember <hi>Eſau,</hi> who after he had deſpiſed his Birthright, <hi>ſought it carefully with teares, but there was no place found for his repentance:</hi> And do not think it will be ſufficient for you to deny bowing unto the Images and Idols of the Nation, while ye live openly in the ſame abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of thoſe which went before, for the voice ſaith, <hi>Be ye ſeparated, and touch no unclean thing, and I will accept you, ſaith the Lord,</hi> which the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in you ſearch whether it be not ſo as I ſay, and have ſaid, in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and let Judgement paſs upon the head of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor in you, that the oppreſſed Seed of God may go free to Reigne and Rule over you and in you for ever; for <hi>Sion</hi> is to be redeemed by Judgement, and her Converts with righteouſneſſe; and the Prophet ſaid, <hi>He would bear the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Lord, becauſe he had ſinned againſt him.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give up freely to the judgement, that ye may reape righteouſneſſe, for God hath ſaid, that judgement ſhall be given for a Light to the people, and truly the judgements of the Lord are true, and righteous altogether, for by them is thy ſervant forewarned. I call Heaven and earth to record this day, That you are truly and faithfully war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to fly, and eſcape the evil to come, and life and death is ſet before you, and if ye chuſe the Light ye ſhall live, for the Light is the life of men, but if ye refuſe to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by it, then darkneſs ſhall be your habitation for ever; for a true Jubilee and releaſe is tendred unto you of the Lord, freedome from bondage and corruption within and and without; and if ye reject this glorious freedome, even freedome from your old maſter, which is ſin and Satan, then hear ye the word of the Lord, <hi>ye ſhall be boared through the eare, and be made to ſerve your old Maſter for ever;</hi> not one jot or tittle of this which is here written ſhall paſs away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulfilled, be it with you or againſt you, I ſhall be cleare of your bloud before the Lord for ever, &amp; God will be Juſtified, and glorified in all, <hi>Even in them which believe, and in them which periſh.</hi> Think not that going unto the Temple once
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53099:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> or twice a week, and there to hear what a man hath ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died in his own will and time will ſerve turn, nay, nor yet the taking of <hi>Davids</hi> words and ſinging of them, who was a man of a true penitent heart before the Lord, who faſted, cryed and mourned becauſe of his tranſgreſſions, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his Couch with his teares, yea, and ſo abhorred all workers of iniquity, that he ſaid, <hi>He would not keep a lyar in his houſe;</hi> which is far wide from your ſtate, who take his words, and ſay you <hi>are not puft in mind, you have no ſcornfull eye,</hi> and you have faſted untill one may number your bones, and you have roared for the diſquietneſſe of your hearts; and are you not a company of liars, and offer a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of lies unto the Lord? And do you not think the Lord will Judge you for theſe things? Yea verily; do you not read, <hi>That all liars ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> and no liars can enter into the holy habitation and reſt of God? Conſider theſe things, and lay them to heart, and put away lying out of your mouths, as you deſire to be accepted of God, and no longer ſay you Sing to the praiſe and glory of God, and the comfort of your own ſouls, when your Singing is to the diſhonour of God, ſuch ſacrifices are an abomination unto the Lord: But whoſo cometh before him, though never ſo ſimple, <hi>Yet if he have clean hands, and a pure heart,</hi> even he who ſpeaks the truth from his heart, ſhall and will be accepted of him, for it is truth in the inward part God onely delights in, without which there is no acceptance: Were not they condemned of the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>Who came before him as his people did, and heard his word, and it was unto them as a very lovely ſong,</hi> yet (their hearts being after their covetouſneſs) availed them nothing? and you never yet came ſo far as this, to wit, to delight to hear the word of the Lord, <hi>which is like a fire and a Hammer</hi> as hath been ſaid; but inſtead of it ye call the letter the Word, whereas the letter ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is the Word,</hi> yet if you were come to hear the word of God and do it not, all would availe you nothing: And you to take Bread and give it one to another, and call it a Sacrament, which word you have no where in the Scripture, neither was ſuch a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53099:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> thing ever commanded to Drunkards, Swearers, Liars and the like, but to thoſe who in faithfulneſs of heart had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken all to follow Chriſt; he brake bread amongſt them, and gave it them as a ſigne of his true Body, and bad them do it <hi>in remembrance of him untill he came,</hi> and when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance came againe amongſt them, there was no more need of any outward ſhadow or figure, which thing they did really witneſſe ſhortly after; but you are breaking bread all the dayes of your lives, and never witneſs him come, as they did, <hi>Even the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvation,</hi> who are pleading for ſin as long as you live; and <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſpeaketh unto them of it, who did alſo abuſe it; and therefore in his next Epiſtle he tels them, and bids them, <hi>Try and prove themſelves, if Christ were not in them, they were reprobates.</hi> So read with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſider, If all were reprobates who did not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Chriſt in them, little will it availe you to take bread and wine, and eat it in imitation of what Chriſt did to his Diſciples, which thing was neither commanded them, nor any who live in ſin; but the true followers of the lamb did, and do <hi>ſhew forth the Lords death,</hi> in eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in all their actions, and their moderation appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto all men, which ſheweth forth both his death and life in them; <hi>So they brake their bread from houſe to houſe with ſingleneſſe of heart, which is the thing the Lord delighteth in above all ſacrifice whatſoever;</hi> and ſuch came to witneſs Chriſt in them to be their life, and all in all, and this witneſſing (in deed and in truth) is a true regenerate ſtate, and Chriſtians life, which is more then to talke, or taking a little water and ſprinkling it upon the face of a child, &amp; ſay it is a ſeal of the Covenant, and an entrance into the Church; which is but a Popiſh trick and invention to deceive the hearts of the ſimple, feeding them with a name, but not of the nature, which thing hath been ſufficiently ſpoken of already: Neither is there any one example in the Scripture for ſuch practiſe. Search, and ſo read, and conſider what you are a doing, for it is high time, for of a truth the mighty and terrible day of the Lord is at hand, <hi>Wherein all ſhall be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53099:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> judged according to the deeds done in the body, whether good or evil:</hi> Therefore be ye awakened, and repent, and think not that a man or Miniſter, made in the will of men, that can preach unto you about an hours ſpace by the houre glaſſe once or twice a week, will ſerve your turn; which thing is a ſtink and a ſhame to all who are true Chriſtians, and ſheweth plainly that ſuch have not the unlimited Spirit of God, which cannot be limitted to a glaſſe, time, or place, but ſpeaketh in whom he will, where he will, and as long as he will. And this was the true order amongſt the Saints in their aſſemblies, not to quench the Spirit of God, but the Spirit of the Prophets were ſubject unto the Prophets; ſo that if any thing was revealed to one that ſat by, <hi>the firſt was to hold his peace;</hi> and they might all Prophecy one by one, and were not forbidden, that all might be edified, and did not maintaine an hireling to ſpeak unto them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hour; and if any were moved to ſpeak in that time, to call it a diſturbance and inſolence, nay, nay, in theſe your fruits and practices you have not ſo much as a forme of godlineſſe, much leſſe the power, as you your ſelves confeſſe; you have not the Spirit of God, which is the power in all the true Chriſtians, and was the fruits and effects of the true living Faith, without which they could not pleaſe God, even the Faith which layeth hold on the promiſe of the Father, which is that the holy Spirit, even the comforter ſhould come unto them, which ſhould lead them into all truth, and ſhew them things to come. And this doth all come to witneſſe, who come to know the onely one and true Baptiſme, which is by one Spirit baptized into one body, which doth not only ſerve to the waſhing away of the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, even purified from dead works, whereby they come to ſerve and worſhip the living God in Spirit and in truth, and ſuch onely doth he ſeek to worſhip him.</p>
            <p>So come away out of all the beggarly Elements (which are to periſh in the uſing) to ſerve the Lord in newneſs of mind, without which all your profeſſion and Religion is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53099:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> but in vaine, for then, and not till then will ye come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a bridle to your tongue, which bridle ye muſt come to witneſs in you, even the light which condemneth you for every idle word and action, and all the works of the fleſh, which are theſe, envy, pride, malice, covetouſneſſe, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, railing, back-biting, evil ſpeaking, drunkenneſs, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, uncleanneſſe, and all uncharitableneſs; <hi>and they who do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God,</hi> Gal. 5.19. Therefore go ye not forth, <hi>for the Kingdome of Heaven is in you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; and as you come to give up to his pure Light, you will be levened into its own nature, and ſo be made partakers of it, which conſiſteth not in word, but in power, holineſſe, peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt; which is the deſire of my ſoul that you (even my Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) may be made partakers of, that ye may witneſs your converſation to be in Heaven, and be no longer ſayers, but doers of the pure holy will of God, that ye may partake of the everlaſting bleſſing, which the Lord hath prepared for all who fear him, even ſuch everlaſting happineſs as ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive the unſpeakable glory which he hath in ſtore for ſuch who give and offer their bodies as living ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, daily to do his will in; <hi>For truly the ſufferings of this preſent world, are not worthy to be compared to the glory, which is, and ſhall be revealed in all ſuch:</hi> And this I do not ſpeak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe another hath ſpoken it, but by true and daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, through ſufferings I have found and felt: And I ſay, that ye may partake of the ſame (with me) in this the day of Gods eternal power, is the ſimple deſire of my heart to God for you, and I know if ye reject not his loving mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and counſel which is freely tendred unto you, in and through me, ye ſhall not come ſhort of the good things of God, for the Lord hath ſhewed it unto me. Therefore come away and give up to God, and crowned ſhall ye be by him for ever, which is a word of eternal truth unto you all; <hi>In his houſe there are many manſions, and if it were not ſo,</hi> I would not ſay it, my ſoul hath richly fed thereon: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I, through the Spirit of my Father, invite you, that we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53099:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> may all come to feed at one table together, and that ye may no longer feed at the table of the Devill.</p>
            <p>Therefore embrace and accept Gods love, that ye may eat of the banquet which is prepared, and that God hath ſent me forth to invite you to; O make not any excuſe, leaſt ye be rejected and not found worthy, there is yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and room to ſpare, and if ye refuſe, others ſhall be conſtrained to come in, even thoſe who ſtand in the high ways and hedges, and ye be ſhut out for evermore with <hi>the fooliſh Virgins;</hi> but be ye wiſe and watch, that ye may have your Lamps trimmed, that when the cry is made at mid-night ye may enter in with the Bride, ſo will ye be found worthy to eat and drink at his table, of his own ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual food, even of his own body, and drink of his own blood, and will witneſſe life in you, life I ſay immortall, and will be leavened into his own nature, even into a new lump, and ſo you being many will come to be one bread, and will be built up together, a ſpiritual houſe holy and accepted, where the Lord will take delight to dwell, and make his abode for evermore; and this onely is the true bleſſed ſtate, which my Soul deſireth ye may come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in deed, and in truth, who am a true lover of all Souls.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53099:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Word unto you who call your ſelves the Miniſters of Christ.</head>
            <p>IS it not a ſhame unto you who call your ſelves by the name of the Miniſters of Chriſt to preach by an hour-glaſſe, and pray by a book? doth not this clearly and plainly manifeſt you are not Miniſters of Chriſt, nor of the Spirit, who doe thus? where have you any example in Scripture for theſe things done by the Saints? who were Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Spirit, and not of the Letter, who ſaid they were not Miniſters of the Letter, but you would ſo have it, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the holy Spirit of God, as your practiſes are ſeen to doe, that limit it to an hours time, and place, and ſo long it ſhould ſpeak, and no longer; O take ſhame upon your ſelvs for theſe things, and Repent, and ceaſe from deceiving the people with your vain cuſtomes and traditions, and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money of the people for ſo doing, which they, or any who can but read may doe as well as you, to take a weeks time or thereabout to ſtudy or compact a company of words together, even as many as you can well ſpeak in an hours time, part you ſteal out of the Scriptures, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part out of other mens writings, and adde your own meanings unto them, and ſo boaſt of other mens lines made ready unto your hands, and have not the word from the Lord, but ſteal it from your Neighbour: Therefore the hand and arm of the Almighty is againſt you, and will lay your ſhame, nakedneſſe, and deceit, open unto all people, that they may no longer be deceived by you: Did not the Apoſtles (who were true teachers of God) <hi>ſpeak as the Spirit of God gave them utterance,</hi> and ſung with the Spirit, and with underſtanding, and prayed with the Spirit, and with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? and can any be ſaid to be true Miniſters of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt but ſuch? Oh! how hath the day of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53099:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lord over taken you as a thief in the night? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your deeds of darkneſſe are made manifeſt and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ye found not to be ſavers, but deceivers of Souls, being ſuch who teach for Doctrine your own inventions and traditions, and ſo the peoples fear towards God is taught by the traditions of men, as Chriſt ſaid; and if any one be moved of the Lord to ſpeak to you or the people, while you are in your high places, you are the firſt which will cry to the people to take him away; was this the Apoſtles exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who bid, if any thing was revealed unto him which ſate by, the firſt was to hold his peace? or is it not the example and practiſe of the perſecuting ſpirit, whoſe works and deeds are wrought in the dark, and are affraid that the light ſhould reprove them? How can ye ſay unto your hearers and followers as the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt did, <hi>Be ye followers of us as we are of Chriſt?</hi> whoſe examples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth yours every way, for he ſaid unto his Diſciples; that <hi>they ſhould be hated of all men for his name ſake, and perſecuted, and caſt out of the Synagogues,</hi> and the like; ſee and try if your fruit be not like unto thoſe who caſt out, and not like unto thoſe who were caſt out: And the Apoſtle ſaid the man of God ſhould not ſtrike, but be humble, and ſhould in meekneſſe inſtruct thoſe which did oppoſe him; this was the fruit and practiſe of the true miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, who in all things walked for to be good examples to others, bearing their faithful witneſſe againſt all ſin, and ſaid, that no unclean thing could enter into the kingdome of Heaven, and bid people walk as they had them for an example; but you inſtead of bearing witneſs againſt all ſin, tell people that they cannot but commit ſin as long as they live, &amp; you your ſelves being examples of pride to them and immoderation, maintaining your wives and children in pride and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſettling your ſelves in ſuch and ſuch places, as may make beſt for your maintainance, and the like, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainly you are not like Chriſt nor his Miniſters who went about ſeeking thoſe that were loſt, being ſuch that were caſt in priſons, in perſecution, in hunger, in cold, in want, and in diſtreſſe, and all for the good of others; in theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53099:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> did the true Miniſters of Chriſt glory, and did not get into a place, &amp; there ſettle themſelvs at their own wil to preach to this or that people, but as the Lord did ſend and direct them they were to go, whether in life or in death, bond, or priſon, yea, wo were to them if they did not doe it; and again, they preached to the people nothing but what they had ſeen, taſted, and had handled of the word of life, and that only did they miniſter unto others; but if you ſhould preach no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what you did witneſſe in this nature (which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true Miniſter of Chriſt ought to doe) and no more, then you might ſtop your mouths, and indeed untill then it would be a thouſand fold better for you ſo to doe; for your condemnation would not be ſo great if you did not preſume thus to teach the people the knowledge of God and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wayes, but did ſit down and labour with your own hands for your livings; for of a truth you doe but adde to your condemnation in this ſtate you are in, as your fruits manifeſt to your faces: Can you look upon your aſſemblies &amp; not bluſh, and be aſhamed to ſee the fruits of your miniſtry in pride, luſt and ambition? dreſſed more like antiques, than ſober moral men, ful of vain talk, and fooliſh jeſting, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying, and all manner of vice is to be found amongſt them, even amongſt your conſtant hearers, whom you call Reformers of Religion; but what they are reformed from (in nature) let the pure light of Chriſt Jeſus judge in all their conſciences, as it doth for God againſt them and you; and I am ſure it ſheweth that they differ nothing in nature from the common practiſe of the Nation, but rather through them and their ungodly practiſes, cauſe the good way of God to be evil ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>And this, O ye Prieſts, is the manifeſt and evident fruits of your work and labour; but the free and true miniſtry of Chriſt Jeſus was for the perfecting of the Saints, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying of the body, untill they all come to a perfect man, <hi>into the meaſure and ſtature of the fulneſſe of Christ,</hi> who was and is head of their body, unto which no corrupt nor prophane member can be joyned; and thus your miniſtry differeth from the true, yea, even as much as light from darkneſſe;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53099:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> the one teacheth and leadeth out of all ſin, and the other teacheth that there can never be a freedome from ſin in this li e, though the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>ye being made free from ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the ſervants of righteouſneſs, for while ye were ſervants unto ſin ye were free from righteouſneſs,</hi> ſo there was the fruits and effects of the true miniſtry, and the fruits and effects of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Satan is ſo far from this, that they preach up ſin for term of life, as hath been ſpoken of already.</p>
            <p>Therefore, O ye Prieſts, be ye warned of the Lord God of life, and ceaſe thus from deluding the people, <hi>and let him that ſtole ſteal no more, but rather let him labor, working with his hands the thing which is good, that he might have to give to him that needeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is counſel of life unto you all, O ye <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prieſts in <hi>France,</hi> I ſay, ceaſe from ſtealing other mens words and making merchandiſe of them to others, but come to the light your ſelves, that ye may hear and learn of Chriſt your ſelves, and then if he pleaſeth to ſend any of you forth to open the blind eyes, and turn the people from darkneſſe to light, and from Satans power to God, then obey his voyce, and go forth freely, and preach as he hath given you freely, ſo will ye profit the people, though this manner of call will be contrary to your own wills, and againſt mens wills ye come to preach to; and till you come to witneſſe this only holy and true call, I ſay again, and again, as from the Lord God of life, ceaſe and be ſtill, and let the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, until the Lord ſend labourers amongſt them, for the Vineyard is only his to ſend into it to labour who he only will appoint thereto, and he which goeth and is not ſent, is but a thief and a robber; which is the word of the Lord God unto all Prieſts of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Therefore ceaſe, ceaſe and repent, that ye may find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for the blood of one man if it be laid to your charg, will be too heavy for you to beare, which aſſuredly ye muſt for many, if ye refuſe to hearken unto the counſell of God, which he in the infiniteneſſe of his love tendereth unto you, for know the end of the true Miniſtry is to bring people unto God, and on him alone to wait for teaching, which is his Covenant and promiſe to bring people to be ſenſible of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53099:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> gift of the holy Spirit of God in themſelves; and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>every man hath a manifeſtation of the Spirit given to him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit withall,</hi> which being turned unto to profit, is a ſufficient teacher of it ſelf, &amp; ſuch need not mans teaching any more, and ſo people come to know their bodies to be the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God through the Spirit which dwelleth in them, and ſo they come to bring forth the fruits of the Spirit, <hi>which are love, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, patience,</hi> and the true reconciliation by Chriſt Jeſus between God and man, the enmity being ſlaine upon the Croſſe, and of twaine one new man is witneſſed, and ſo peace comes to be witneſſed with God, and not before, and untill the new creature be witneſſed all availeth nothing; but the true and everlaſting Miniſtry of Chriſt Jeſus bringeth the creature unto this, and none elſe, by which and in which the creature comes to bring forth naturally the fruits of the Spirit, as he did the fruits of the fleſh before, which was nothing elſe but luſt and uncleanneſſe, and filthineſſe of life: So give up to be taught by him in this the day of his Almighty power.</p>
            <p>Therefore let this be a warning unto all Prieſts, Let God alone with his own work, for he needeth no mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to help him, for the beſt of your ſtuff you have is but compacted with your own natural wiſdome, which you muſt all looſe, before you can come to know God, <hi>For man by wiſdome knows not God, neither can the natural man diſcerne the things of the Spirit, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye muſt all come to the teachings of the Spirit of God your ſelves, before you can come to teach others. Theſe things are plaine and manifeſt unto every one who is not wilfully blind, and drunk with prejudice; therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>Paul</hi> had more to loſe of this kind then moſt of you have, yet he ſaid he counted it gaine to loſe it all to gaine Chriſt; and let him be your example, who reaſoned not with fleſh and blood, but immediately obeyed the Heavenly voice. I ſpeak this unto you in love, and ſome of you the Lord may make Inſtruments in his glorious worke in this the day of his power, if ye reject not his loving counſel, and viſitation of love, which to you is tendred in particular,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53099:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> O ye Prieſts of this Nation, to whom this is ſent: But if ye reject his counſel, and will have none of his reproof, then hear what the Spirit of the Lord ſaith, the Lord will make you examples of his wrath above many; and that is a word of truth unto you all, that ye may truly be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and repent before it be too late. And I warne you as from the Lord God of Heaven and earth, that ye be not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of ſtopping this from paſſing amongſt the people, by rejecting it or caſting an odium upon it, thereby to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the peoples minds againſt the truth of God, and things that do belong to your peace, which if you do, better were it that a milſtone were hanged about your necks, and you caſt into the midſt of the Sea, then you ſhould hinder the leaſt from receiving this teſtimony, for Gods dreadfull and terrible day is at hand, in which he will render to every one according to the fruits of his own doings, both Prieſts and people, for every one ſhall give an account of himſelf to God, and every one ſhall die for his own iniquity. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againe, and againe I ſay be ye warned; and if ye Prieſts, or any of you ſhall hearden your hearts againſt this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of love from the Lord which is ſent amongſt you, by eſteeming that you are the true Miniſters of Chriſt, and the ſpiritual weaponed men, then come forth openly into the field, and make it appear, by anſwering the Queries which are propounded unto you in this book, that ye may through it come to underſtand, and the truth may yet be made further manifeſt in the eyes of all: And this proffer do not ſlight leaſt the people grow jealous of you; but this I ſay in love to your immortal ſouls, happy will ye be if ye receive the love of God in it, and ſubmit unto his holy will, and receive his counſel, and be adviſed betimes, for the fruits of your Miniſtry doth teſtifie to your faces, that it is not of God, for if it were, it would turn the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the evil of their wayes, and from Satan to God: <hi>My little children,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, of whom I travail in birth againe untill Chriſt be formed in you;</hi> Mark the words, and conſider them, Chriſt was to be formed in them; and this was the true Saints and Chriſtians life to witneſſe him to rule and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53099:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Reigne in them, for ſaith <hi>Paul I live, yet not I, but Chriſt in me;</hi> ſo in the Saints was the only hope of their glory, and without this, all are without the true hope, and God in this world, which is the unregenerate ſtate, where the new birth and creature is not witneſſed nor known, but are captives unto ſin, and Satan, luſt and uncleanneſſe; but where Chriſt is witneſſed <hi>the body is dead becauſe of ſin, and the ſpirit is life becauſe of righteouſneſs:</hi> And bleſſed are they who witneſſe this in deed and in truth; ſuch are the <hi>true Iſraelites in whom there is no guile,</hi> which the Lord of glory delights in, but abhorreth all faire ſayers and not doers, ſuch ſhall have their portion with the hypocrites and unbeleevers for ever; but whoſoever heareth the ſayings of the Lord and doth them, he is like unto a wiſe man which built and founded his houſe upon a Rock, which the ſtormes could not move; and they are Heirs of happineſſe for evermore, (world without end) Crowned with the faithfull for ever; <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen,</hi> even only thoſe who are faithfull; therefore I ſay againe (through the Spirit) bleſſed and happy are they world without end: And that many of you might come to enjoy this eternal bleſſed and happy end, I could lay down my life were it required of me. Conſider, will a call ſave you? nay: Therefore conſider <hi>what will it availe you, to gaine the whole world, and loſe your own ſouls</hi> for the tranſitory pleaſures of this fading world: O let it never be, but embrace mercy while it is freely tendred unto you, and ye will enjoy an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible Crown, which the Lord hath in ſtore for all who forſake all corruptible things for his ſake. And theſe are words and counſel of life unto you all, which ſpringeth from the true fountain of life and love, which you will come to witneſs.</p>
            <p>And truly friends, there is no life but through death, nor no Crown but through the Croſſe, nor no victory but through War and tribulation of the Lamb: And conſider <hi>the Lamb was ſlaine from the foundation of the world;</hi> and the world is ſet in mans heart, <hi>And the whole world lyeth in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, for it is in you the Lamb is ſlaine,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53099:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> even in ſpirituall <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt:</hi> Behold a Miſtery, read and conſider, ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> even idleneſs and fullneſſe of bread, and adultery, and the like, and this crucifieth the juſt in you daily; and if ever you turn to the Light of Chriſt in you, you will witneſſe my words to be true, and will come to <hi>mourn over him whom we have pierced, even as a man mourneth over his only begotten ſon;</hi> for truly untill you come here, ye remain guilty of the blood of the Son of God, and all mankind upon the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>And theſe few words was I moved of the Lord to write unto you, that ye may conſider well your ſtate, and read within your ſelves with the Light, whether it be ſo, or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So God Almighty open and pierce through your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, that ye may perfectly come to ſee and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend with all Saints, what is the miſtery and love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, concerning you and all mankind; which is the true deſire of him who is ready to lay down his life for his vileſt enemies. And ſeriouſly conſider, whether the world ſtands not yet whole in you, which is truly to be deſtroyed, even by fire, as truly as the old was by water, and untill this be witneſſed, the juſt in you ſuffereth, for it is the juſt that ſuffereth by the unjuſt in the particular, as well as in the general. Ponder theſe things well, and truly weigh them, and the juſt in you will anſwer to my words, from whence they come, and to what end they are ſpoken; and ſo will ye find mercy, and not till then, profeſſe what ye will, for except ye witneſs Chriſt riſen in you, all Preaching and Profeſſion is in vaine whatſoever. Theſe are perfect and true ſayings, and will ſtand a witneſſe againſt you for ever if ye reject them; for if you will or dare come to your tryall, it will be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proved that you are not the true and faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt, neither by Call, Maintainance, nor manner of worſhip, as Preaching, Praying, or Singing, Baptiſme or any other thing, which is uſed or taught by you, or amongſt you, neither have you any part of it by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or example in the Scripture of truth; therefore it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53099:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> upon you, to ſhew who were your firſt authors and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for all the cuſtomes and traditions you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, ſinging one part of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms with your hats off, and reading another part with your hats on, and putting them in Meeter like Ballads, by which meanes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to ſing that which they never came to witneſſe, as hath been before ſpoken of; and your Sacraments, and ſuch like, which ye have not one word in the Scripture for. Therefore come forth and ſhew openly who were the firſt inventers of theſe things, reading over a company of Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters when you come together, and the like; all theſe things (when they and you come to be weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary) will be found too light, and far ſhort of the true worſhip of God, who is not to be worſhipped any other way then in Spirit and in Truth; and in that one Spirit, if any had a Pſalm or Hymn, or Prayer, or Praiſes, he did it, and ſung it to the praiſe and true glory of God; and this was the true order of the Saints, and not to take another mans words for Pſalm, or Praiſe, or Prayer, and ſay it over, nay theſe things are an abominable abomination unto the Lord, for it is the Spirit onely which maketh interceſſion for the true children and ſervants of God, for it alone know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our wants, and is many times poured forth unto the Lord <hi>with ſighes and groanes which cannot be uttered,</hi> and this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuch like Sacrifices doth God accept; not for Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Swearers, Lyars, and all manner of unclean perſons to take the Saints words in their mouths, and come before him with them, Gods ſoul abhorreth it. So all that ever is practiſed amongſt you will be found to be but in ſin, your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatizing and falling away from the true faith, which was propheſied both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſhould come, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The night cometh, wherein no man can work,</hi> in which time (becauſe of iniquity) the love of many ſhall wax cold: And this is the fruits and marks of that day, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw them coming in his time, even thoſe who ſhould teach things they ought not for filthy lucres ſake, yea, and before his deceaſe ſo grievous was the falling away, that he ſaid all <hi>Aſia</hi> was turned from him: and alſo to <hi>Timothy</hi> he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53099:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> propheſied of theſe things plainly, that men ſhould heap up to themſelves teachers, having itching eares, and ſhould not endure ſound Doctrine, and the like, which ye may ſee in the many teachers come up, and made by, and in the will of men, according to their own luſt; which anſwereth unto Chriſts word, who ſaid many ſhould come and ſay <hi>Lo here is Chriſt, or Lo, he is there, believe them not</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for the Kingdome of Heaven is within you:</hi> Mark, <hi>and ſuch ſhall deceive the very Elect if it were poſſible,</hi> but it is impoſſible to deceive them, for ſuch are Chriſts ſheep, who know his voice, and a ſtranger they will not follow: But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits;</hi> ſo by their fruits muſt we try them now, for ſuch teachers as men doe heap up to themſelves are ſeen in the light, which tryeth your Prieſts, who preach up ſin and luſt as long as men live; ſo here you are tryed and found to be ſuch who are choſe in mens will; but Chriſts ſheep hear his voyce, and obey it, and follow him, who leadeth into all purity and holineſſe. And thus are all diſtinguiſhed and known by their fruits, as Chriſt hath ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we ſhould therefore conſider theſe things, and lay them to heart, and repent before it be too late: This word doth the Lord often put in my heart towards you, for dreadful and terrible is the day which is already dawned over your heads. The voyce of the true Shepherd ſaith <hi>Come, Come freely, without money and without price, and let him that heareth come, and let him that is a thirſt come, and whoſoever will let him take of the water of life freely; and let him that will, buy Wine and Milk without money and without price. Why will ye ſpend your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not?</hi> Incline your eares, and your Souls ſhall live, and your Souls ſhall delight themſelves in fatneſſe. This is the voyce of the true Shepherd to all the inhabitants of the Earth, therefore <hi>whilſt it is ſaid to day, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation,</hi> but away all to the fountain which is freely ſet open to waſh away ſin and tranſgreſſion, <hi>for you have all forſaken the fountain of living waters, and have hewen out Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns that hold no water; ſaith the Lord, every one is gone aſtray after the imagination of his own heart; and the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53099:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord hath looked down from his holy habitation, and beheld there is none that ſeeketh after him amongſt the ſons of men,</hi> who are thus degenerated from him; for though he hath created man upright, yet he hath found out many inventions, (one thing being neglected) by which meanes he is become more ſtrang to his Creator than the Ox to his owner, or the Aſſe to his maſters crib.</p>
            <p>Sad and deplorable eſtate miſerable man is fallen into, running on greedily in the way of deſtruction, and drinking in iniquity as the Ox drinketh water, and yet will ſeeme to lean upon the Lord, and ſay, is not the Lord amongſt us? though they forſake him, and refuſe his tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, and caſt his holy Law behind their backs, and will none of his reproof, and make unto themſelves Laws, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and ordinances, which will ſute moſt unto their luſts, and heap up to themſelves teachers, having itching eares, even ſuch as they make in their own will, who preach for hire, and divine for money, which was alwaies an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing unto the Lord, who ſent his holy ſervants and Prophets to cry againſt ſuch things; yet do the ſons of men delight to have it ſo: And ſuch teachers as theſe cry, peace, peace, to the wicked, and ſay no evil ſhall come upon them ſo long as they put into their mouths, but otherwiſe ſuddenly prepare warre againſt you, as the tryal will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the ſame; and they with great ſwelling words of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty promiſe to others liberty, while they themſelves are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants unto corruption; and ſuch like do people chooſe unto themſelves, becauſe they propheſie ſmooth things unto them, and under their teachings they can live as they liſt, in pride, covetouſneſſe, wantonneſſe, and all manner of evil all the dayes of their lives, as their fruits manifeſt, telling people they cannot but ſin as long as they live; by which means (inſtead of turning people from their wickedneſs) they ſtrengthen their hands in it, which ſheweth plainly they are ſuch who ran when the Lord never ſent them, therefore they do not profit the people at all, who are ever learning of them but never able to come unto the knowledg of the truth, which makes free all who come unto it, as ſaith Chriſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53099:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> Jeſus, if you know the truth, the truth ſhall make you free. And the Apoſtles were ſent to turn people from darkneſſe to light, and from Satans power to God, which was the effect of the true and free Miniſtry of Chriſt, even to open the blind eyes, and make blind thoſe which could ſee. So they who come to be turned from Satans power unto God, come to be turned from darkneſſe to light, which is a turning from ſinne to righteouſneſſe, and here the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to be profited; but ſuch hirelings who run and are not ſent, they neither bring the people to the light, nor from ſin to righteouſneſs, being Miniſters of darkneſs themſelves, and Preach for filthy lucre ſake, and do in no wiſe profit the people; as I have ſaid, if one come amongſt them and their hearers, and do but declare, and ſpeak of thoſe things unto them wherewith Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightned him, then preſently they fall upon him commonly by the command of their Prieſts, and cry out he is a deceiver, away with him, though they have nothing to be deceived of but ſin, and uncleanneſs; which ſheweth plainly they are not of the number of the Elect of God, for they need not to fear being deceived, for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to deceive them, <hi>For Chriſts ſheep hear his voice, and knoweth it, and a ſtranger will they not follow:</hi> But theſe, like blind men, inſtead of <hi>trying all things, and holding faſt that which is good,</hi> ſtop their ears, and furiouſly run themſelves upon a poore ſimple innocent man, who ſeeks not theirs, but them: And this their fruits manifeſts they are not in the nature of the true Chriſtians, but of the <hi>Jews, who perſecuted the Prophets, and ſtoned them who were ſent unto them;</hi> and in this nature do they ſing, pray, and the like, which is no more accepted of the Lord, <hi>Then if they cut off a Dogs neck, or offer a ſacrifice of blood,</hi> for ſuch was <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice, <hi>who was of the envious one, who ſlew his brother.</hi> And this is the fruits and effects of the hirelings Miniſtry, which is a griefe unto the upright in heart to ſee: And behold, how poor people are kept in bondage, and from the knowledge of God by them, hearing and learning from their youth up, untill they go to the grave, and ſtill in ſin, and pleading for it as long as they live.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:53099:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>O people, it is high time to awake and conſider theſe things, and lay them to heart, for the Ax of the Lord is a laying to the roote of every tree, <hi>And every tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not forth good fruit, ſhall be cut down and caſt into the fire,</hi> for the Lord hath long born with you, and men have concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nought but vanity, and brought forth lies, and every one is ſtriving either by deceit or policy, to uphold his own way by the arm of fleſh, and he that can get the power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand, oppreſſeth all who will not bow unto his manner or forme of worſhip, as though God were ſerved in mans will, or could or would be limitted by the ſons of men, while every one is crying up his own way to be beſt, while they are all in the way of ſin, pleading for it as long as they live. The Lords ſoul abhorreth theſe things, for it is only the ſacrifice of <hi>clean hands and a pure heart</hi> which he accepteth, even of ſuch who are of <hi>an humble and contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at his Word, and ſuch he will in no wiſe deſpiſe:</hi> But how far men are from this ſpirit (which is onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of by the Lord) let the pure Light of Chriſt Jeſus judge in all your conſciences; doth not envy reign ſtill in their hearts, and where that reigneth there is ſtrife, and every evil work, which ſeperateth man from God; and in this ſtate ſhould they ſacrifice <hi>thouſands of Rams, and ten thouſand rivers of Oyle, the fruit of their bodies for the ſins of their ſouls,</hi> it would availe them nothing: <hi>But waſh you, make you clean, ſaith the Lord; and put away the evil of your doings; relieve the fatherleſs and the widdow, and I will accept you; and though your ſins are as red as ſcarlet, yet will I make them as white as ſnow.</hi> Saith <hi>Solomon, he which confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſin ſhall find mercy,</hi> and it is certain that none elſe doth, or ever ſhall, for the ſacrifices of the wicked are an abomination unto the pure God: For when the <hi>Jews</hi> were in the obſervation of ſacrifices, Sabbaths, New-moons, and the like, the Lord ſaid <hi>they were an abomination, and loathſomneſs unto him, and his ſoul did abhor them,</hi> and the reaſon was becauſe of the evil of their doings, for in ſuch things the Lord delighteth not; but a body which is prepared to do his will in, is only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for there he only takes delight to dwell, which is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53099:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> more then all ſacrifices, offerings and oblations, which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> knew right well: But this thing Satan and his Miniſters Preach not to the people, that he may keep his ſeat whole within them; profeſs what they will in words he matters it not, for he knows if once the creature cometh to the Covenant of God, that then he will come to witneſſe his body to be his Temple, as he hath promiſed, <hi>I will dwell in them and walk in them;</hi> therefore Satan ſtrives every way to keep people from the light which is the Covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men would come to know the teachings of God, and would not need that man ſhould teach them: But this makes not for the hireling, nor his profit, therefore would he be Maſter as much as in him lieth, telling people they muſt not look for God to ſpeak unto men in theſe days, and that revelations are ceaſed, and ſuch like ſtuff he filleth up his hours time with, which ſheweth he and his hearers know not the Son of God as the true Chriſtians did: And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>unto thoſe that come unto me I give eternal life;</hi> and none hath eternal life but thoſe <hi>who know the Father, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So all Prieſts and people this is to you, and ſheweth that you are from the true Faith, and to every good work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, for he that doth not witneſs all his works done and wrought in him by the vertue and power of God, all his works are but as filthy rags, which is ſelf righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, for if the juſt do not work in the creature, it is ſelf, which can never be accepted of the Father, for the true children of God came to witneſſe that God did all their works for them and in them, and ſo did witneſſe in deed and in truth, the Lord to be their righteouſneſs, and were called by that name. So come and try your works, and by whom they are wrought in you, if not by Chriſt, then it is ſelf, and ſo it will availe you nothing, <hi>For without me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye can do nothing: I am the Vine</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and ye are the branches, and my Father is the husbandman, and every branch which bringeth not forth fruit, my Father cutteth it off, and caſteth it into the fire, but every branch which bringeth forth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more abundantly; ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53099:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> abide in me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the light of the world,</hi> for in him only is their fruit found to be accepted. So read, try, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in whom ye are, and whether ye are in the true Vine, yea, or nay; if not, your ſtate is miſerable, and ye are yet in your ſins.</p>
            <p>Therefore ceaſe from your hireling teachers, and learn of Chriſt the pure light in you, and you will come to witneſs a teacher continually with you, <hi>Which will never be removed into a corner any more; but your ear ſhall hear a voice behind you, ſaying, this is the way, walk in it, turn neither to the right hand, nor to the left;</hi> which if once witneſſed ye will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor all hireling teachers for ever; and being come to know the voice of the true Shepherd of your ſouls, ye will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the pure holy teachings of the holy God, lying down and riſing up, directing you in the pure, holy, and undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led path of peace, in which no Lions whelp can tread; and this to witneſſe is the end of all Miniſtrations, Types, and ſhadows whatſoever, the life and ſubſtance being witneſſed in you, even Chriſt Jeſus the Light, the Covenant of God, which is given a Covenant of Light unto all Nations, that he might be his Salvation unto the ends of the earth; which is the only true Ciſtern that is able to hold water for your ſouls. And <hi>John</hi> did bear witneſs in like manner of him, ſaying, <hi>He was the true light which inlightned every one that came into the world, and the light is the life of men;</hi> and as you come to the light you will witneſs it ſo, and not before ye know his life to abide in you, which light being received and followed, you will receive power to become the ſons of God, even a birth which is not of man, nor of the will of man, but of God, which only is loved; ſo the ſons of God you will witneſſe to be, and his holy Spirit you will be lead by, <hi>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God are the ſons of God, and they who have not the Spirit of Chriſt are none of his:</hi> Therefore I ſay again, and again, try whoſe ye are, for if you have not the Spirit of Chriſt, you are none of the ſons of God, but of the Devil. Theſe are true and plain words unto you all, that ye may not be any longer decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, nor truſt to lying vanities any longer, and forſake
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53099:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> your own mercies, which is freely tendred unto you of the Lord in this the day of his love, wherein he doth invite you freely, to come unto him, <hi>Without money and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pride,</hi> that ye may eat and drink, and be ſatisfied at the Rivers of his pleaſures; and not to ſpend your labour and precious time for nought, for your time is but ſhort, and the meaſure of your iniquitie is even up (amongſt the ſons of men,) and the Angel of his wrath is even ready to ſmite. Therefore be ye ſeparated and touch no unclean thing, and God Almighty will accept you; for verily I have ſeen the wrath of the Lord breaking forth againſt this Nation, and it was very terrible: Therefore ſtand not (as you love your immortal ſouls) to contend about words, or any outward thing; but come to the light, that ye may witneſſe life, that ſo your covering may only be the pure Spirit of the Lord, thereby to have a hiding place in him, elſe the ſword of his indignation and wrath you will never be able to eſcape, but it will cut you off for ever, with all the unclean and uncircumciſed of the earth. Therefore be ye not mockers nor deſpiſers, leaſt ye periſh, for the Lord is working a work in theſe dayes, that ſuch cannot believe, though it were told them; and this is a true warning, and teſtimony of Gods everlaſting love, in and through one that is a witneſs thereof, and a friend to all ſouls.</p>
            <p>And now, that you may read and ſeriouſly conſider, into what a ſad ſtate you are fallen, (from the Image of him that created you) is the deſire of my heart, and come for to be reſtored again into the ſame dominion, for all are degenerated into the plant of a ſtrange Vine, bringing forth wild fruit, contrary to the expectation of the good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and to the grieving of his righteous ſoul; for read and conſider, <hi>He planted a Vineyard, and fenced it about, and pruned it, and cast the ſtones out of it, and expected it ſhould bring forth fruit,</hi> (as I have ſaid,) <hi>but it brought forth wild fruit; what could I have done more for my Vineyard? ſaith the Lord.</hi> Here all the ſons of men may conſider their condition, which is truly ſad and miſerable; though they are ſo ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53099:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> upon the Lees of iniquity, that they do not conſider it; as it is written, <hi>There is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh God, they are all gone out of the way, they have been made altogether unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one, their throat is an open ſepulchre, they have uſed their tongues to deceit, the poiſon of aſpes is under their lips,</hi> Rom. 3.11. <hi>Yea they commit iniquity with greedineſſe,</hi> (even as the Ox drinketh in water) <hi>their table is full of vomit, and there is no ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, they conceive miſchief in the night upon their bed, and riſe early in the morning to put it in practice, and ſay in their hearts, the Lord ſeeth us not, our mouthes are our own, who ſhall us controll? they lye in waite privily for the innocent, and lay a ſnare in ſecret for him.</hi> O! what a ſad and dolefull condition are the ſons of men fallen into! yea there is no fear of God before their eyes, <hi>Eating and drinking and riſing up to play;</hi> marrying and giving in marriage, and all in the luſt and uncleanneſs; the ſeed of the evil one being head in them, nought but pride and oppreſſion is brought forth, envy and malice, yea the beſt of men is but a lyer every one ſeeking by fraud and deceit to exalt his own horn, and ſeeking to maintain his own carkaſe in great honour and dignity, and he which is ſtronger then his neighbour will take all advantages againſt him to bring him under him, and to bow to his will. O woful ſtate and hard to be declared is the degeneration of fallen man from his Creator, who at firſt created him in his own Image and likeneſſe, in holineſſe and purity to reign over all the works of his hands (in the power and wiſdome of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) and had put all things in ſubjection under him, and knew the right uſe of every thing, (he ſtanding in the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and wiſdome of God) and to what end they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, even for them to ſerve his body, and his body to ſerve his ſoul, and his ſoul to ſerve his Creator in the body, and as he thus ſtood in the fear, dominion, and wiſdome of his Lord, all things were bleſſed unto him, and all things were clean and pure; and being guided by the pure holy Spirit of his maker, is counſelled as in the beginning, and hath a law-giver as at the firſt; but when once he gave ear
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53099:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> unto the voyce of the Serpent (who was more ſubtile than any beaſt of the field) conſented to eat of that which was forbidden him (that he ſhould not touch to eat) even of the tree of knowledge of good and evil; let him which readeth underſtand, he had liberty to eat of every tree but that, all being good, and that alſo, for all that which God made was good and bleſſed, but for food it was not to be eaten of nor touched: And as I ſaid, when man once had tranſgreſſed the righteous Law of his Creator, he loſt his glorious Dominion he had, and the pure Spirit of the Lord (by which he was covered) departed from him, ſo that he was naked without a covering, then ſhame entred in upon him, and ſo he went to make unto himſelf other coverings (then thoſe which he had in the beginning) to hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but all in vain: So all the profeſſors in the world who are not covered with the holy Spirit of the Lord, may read, and ſee what they are doing; for this is truely your ſtate and condition, feeding upon your own knowledge which is forbidden, and feeding thereon are thereby ſet on work to make unto your ſelves other coverings then that of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of truth and righteouſneſſe: So read and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when <hi>Adam</hi> had once done ſo, the Lord caſt him out of his Garden, and he loſt his dominion which he had, and God placed Cherubins at <hi>Eden</hi> gate, which turned every way to keep the way of the tree of life, ſo that men could never enter again that way, but through death, even the death of that nature and wiſdom which he fed on, which was of the earth, and is earthly, ſenſuall and deviliſh: So read and conſider, whether you witneſſe this, yea or nay. And ſo man being drove out of the earth, the curſe entred, and the Serpent became head in him; and he that was the ſonne of God before, and was guided by him in all his actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the ſon and ſervant of the Devil, and a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave unto corruption; and thus was the Lamb ſlain, even the juſt ſeed of God became oppreſſed in him, even as a Cart that is loaded with ſheaves, which before bore rule in him wholly; yet the Lord having regard to the works of his hands, and his bowels being moved with pity towards
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53099:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, his mercy being over all the works of his hands, took not his holy ſeed from him, but made a Covenant with man, that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head, which was become head in man then, which promiſe was witneſſed and fulfilled in <hi>Abel,</hi> who was righteous and was accepted, the ſeed of God bearing rule in him, and the ſeed of the envious one was bruſed, which reign'd in his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſo being one with the holy ſeed became a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, and ſuffered by the ſeed of the evil one in his brother; and here was the firſt perſecution, and from that day unto this hath the juſt ſuffered by the unjuſt, the ſeed of the Bond-woman perſecuting the ſeed of the free-woman, which kept the Commandements of God. So here all men may read and ſee what ſtock and generation they are of, and what ſeed is head in them, for one of the two beareth rule in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual man upon the face of the whole earth; where the ſeed of the woman is head there is peace, humility, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, patience, temperance, love to all, bearing, and forbearing, praying for enemies, and ſuffering and enduring all things, not having confidence in the arm of fleſh, nor yet a helper in the earth, not ſeeking revenge, but committeth its innocent cauſe to God, knowing that vengeance belongs only to him, praying for enemies, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to thoſe that deſpitefully uſe them; and this, &amp; this only is the life of the true chriſtian, for in him alone this holy ſeed of God beareth rule, and hath dominion, for they are the peace-makers; but where the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent beareth rule there luſt reigneth, from whence cometh all warre, ſtrife, contention, and debate; and this was <hi>Cains</hi> nature, even to kill and murder, who was a Vagabond drove from God, yet he built him a City, and called it by the name of his ſon, and ſo from this ſtock hath riſen op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and murder, and getting of poſſeſſion in the earth; and this was the fruit and effect of that ſeed which from him ſprung, for which cauſe the holy Spirit of God was grieved from day to day, until it had repented him at the heart that he had made man, which cauſed <hi>Noah</hi> to preach unto them righteouſneſſe, but they rejected his counſel, and would not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53099:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> be warned, but they continued eating and drinking, marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and giving in marriage, all in the luſt and unclean na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which crucified the juſt, and ſo continued until the day of wrathful unreſiſtable vengeance and flood of Gods indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation brake out upon them: And thus in all ages have thoſe in whom this ſeed of enmity hath borne rule provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the holy God to wrath againſt them, yet he forbore with them until they had filled up their meaſure of iniquity, in which time he ſent his holy ſervants the Prophets to warn and forewarn them of the wrath which was due unto the tranſgreſſors, and ſtill as they did reject the councel of the Lord, and his tender reproofs, they felt his heavy hand in the end, for he hath ſaid, <hi>his Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with man;</hi> though men may (as they did then) ſeek by their own ſtrength, policy and wiſdome, to build them a Tower to reach up unto Heaven; but God confounded their deſign, for neither by that way nor by that meanes could they ever bring their purpoſe to paſſe; and from that ſtock came and ſprung all the diviſions upon the face of the earth, one buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this thing, and the other that thing, and all in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, being confounded and diſperſed in their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings by the wiſe God; though vain man may think by ſuch meanes to build him a Tower to reach up to Heaven, but ſuch are the thieves and the robbers which climb up an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way then Chriſt ſpake of, who came not in by the door which is the light, the onely and alone true way to God, and there is not another; but men are ſo hardened, and their underſtandings ſo darkned through the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſin, that though theſe things are plainly written and ſpoken of in the Scriptures, yet they cannot perceive them, the book being become to them a book that is ſealed, which one took and gave another to read and ſaid, I pray thee read it, and he ſaid, I cannot, for it is ſealed, and he gave it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaid, I pray thee read it, and he ſaid I cannot, for I am unlearned; ſo to learned and unlearned it is a miſtery: And truely I freely declare unto all the ſons of men that there is none that can open the ſeals thereof, <hi>neither is there any found worthy in Heaven or in Earth, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lamb
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53099:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God,</hi> the Light of the World, who hath enlightned every one which cometh into the World; and till men come to give up to be led, guided, and directed by this pure Light in all their words and actions, the myſteries of the Kingdome of God, nor godlineſſe they will never come to know nor underſtand, for the vail is over their hearts, and until it be rent and taken away by the power and vertue of the Light, they run on as the <hi>Jews</hi> doe in darkneſſe, and know not at what they ſtumble, for though the miſtery of godlineſſe be great, yet it is but one to all and in all, either <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, even God manifest in the fleſh, the Emanuel, God with us,</hi> even with men and in men, and this is <hi>the Miſtery of Myſteries</hi> which the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>hath been hid from ages and generations, which was Chriſt in them the hope of their glory;</hi> and without this be witneſſed, there is neither true hope nor true glory; though men talk of hope, yet it is but the Hypocrites hope, which periſheth, and will never bring them to glory, no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the earthly, which is but grief and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; but he that hath, and is truly poſſeſſed with the true and living hope abiding in him, purifieth himſelf even as Chriſt is pure, even from all earthly affections, either of glory, honour, or riches, wiſdom, or any other earthly thing, being given up in all things to ſeek the true honour and glory which cometh from God onely, though for ſo doing he may, and is accounted a fool, poor and ſimple, and rejected by thoſe who poſſeſſe onely the falſe hope, who ſeek the riches, honour and praiſe of the Kings and Princes of this world, which are the manifeſt fruits and effects of their hope. And thus is Chriſt become the true riches of the ſoul, and the creatures glory, whereby he comes to tread all other things under his feet, and counts them but as droſſe and dung in compariſon to it.</p>
            <p>So here all may prove and try their hope by its manifeſt and apparent opperations, in brief, the one hoping this and that power will be the chiefeſt, that they may have acceſſe unto it to maintain their Church and Religion, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſiring that God onely may have, and take the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and that he alone may rule and reign, becauſe he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53099:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> knoweth it is in God, and the gates of Hell can never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt it; therefore matters not, nor fears any outward ſtrength, becauſe his ſtrength and hope is in God alone, who purifies and makes clean all who hope and put their truſt in him, by the power of his own ſeed in them, (to rule and reign) which bruiſeth the ſeed and head of the Serpent for ever, and conquers the laſt enemy; and ſuch onely come to witneſſe the true and living birth which is of God, which ſinneth not, and comes to be reſtored into the ſame glorious ſtate and condition as <hi>Adam</hi> was in before he fell.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſubſtance of all words, and alſo it is the end of Chriſts miniſtring, even to bring people unto this, by which they come to know (as I have ſaid) the promiſe of God fulfilled, to wit, the ſeed of the woman to bruiſe the Serpents head, and their bodyes to be Temples and habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God through the Spirit, and he to live and walk in them, as he hath promiſed; but the miniſtry of Satan is to preach up ſin as long as men live, by which means he may keep his Kingdome, for he hath no other Kingdome but it. Therefore let men profeſſe what they will in word, he mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not as long as he hath his Dominion in their hearts, and his head unbruiſed there, where he ſitteth as God, even in the Temple of God; and this is the abomination of deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation amongſt the ſons of men, which is to be made deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in this the day of Gods Almighty power, in which the miſtery of the Man of ſin ſhall be fully revealed and made manifeſt, and the Kingdome of the moſt High ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed with men and in them: And this great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work ſhall not be by might, nor by force of men, but by the arm and Spirit of the Almighty God, whoſe power ſhall be evidently made manifeſt to free and ſet at liberty the ſons of men from the bonds of ſin and corruption, that they may no longer be Satans bond-ſlaves; I ſay all ſuch ſhall come to witneſſe this who ſhall cleave to the Lord with ſincerity of heart, in this the day of his gracious love unto the ſons and daughters of men; but thoſe that reject his love, and will none of his reproof, ſhall witneſſe and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53099:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo feel his power in wrath and dreadful venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, who will aſſuredly render unto them according to their deeds, and ſo much the more as they have ſlighted the day of their viſitation, and rather believed Satan and his meſſengers, that his power is greater to keep them in ſin and bondage, than Gods was to deliver them, though the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf (which they ſeem to profeſſe) beareth witneſſe againſt them: And the Apoſtles Miniſtry was to open the blind eyes, and to turn people from darkneſſe to light, and from Satans power unto God; and they who believe in this Miniſtry and receive it in the love thereof, they come perfectly to know (as they are turned from darkneſs, which is the power of Satan, unto light which is the power of God) and witneſſe in deed and in truth the power of God greater to deliver from ſin, than Satans power is to keep in ſin; therefore the unbeliever and Satan and his Miniſters ſhall all be taken and caſt into the lake of Brimſtone and Fire, and be tormented for ever and ever; and the little ſtone which is cut out of the mountain without hands ſhall become a great mountain, and cover the whole earth for ever, and ſhall grind all his enemies to powder, for God Almighty hath determined it, and his Decree is unalterable.</p>
            <p>Therefore, O thou Nation of <hi>France</hi> in particular, I warn thee as one whom God hath warned and conſtrained ſo to do, that thou ſtand not in the ſtubbornneſſe of thy heart againſt the Lord and his Anointed in this the day of his power, but ſubmit unto him by repentance and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thy ſins, that thou mayſt find mercy, elſe he will teare thee in pieces, and none ſhall be able to deliver thee out of his hands; which is his eternal word unto you all: Therefore lay it to heart, and while you have time prize it, before it be too late. And know ye <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that it is onely the true <hi>Jew</hi> which ſhall have acceptance in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in that day, even they who are of the circumciſion of the heart, who are covered with his holy Spirit, and not with a name to live, and are dead, as it is with you at this day: Therefore this viſitation of love is ſent amongſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53099:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> you, that you may read and conſider your condition, and how you ſtand, that ye may not plead ignorance in the dreadfull day of account, which is even at the door; and remember, <hi>If God ſpared not the natural branches, but cut them off who ſinned, he will not ſpare you, for the ſoul that ſinneth ſhall dye, but he that turneth from his ſins, and doth righteouſneſſe, ſhall live;</hi> and there is no other Covenant or promiſe of God then this. Therefore let not your Preachers deceive you any longer, by telling you, it ſhall go well with you, though you live in ſin and uncleanneſſe; but turn to the light of Chriſt which condemneth you for all ſin, and give up to be guided by it, and it will lead you to forſake your ſins, ſo will you find mercy, elſe you will periſh eternally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is the word of the Lord unto you all; therefore I ſay again, and again, prize Gods love which is freely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unto you; <hi>For a famine of the word of the Lord hath been amongſt men, and the viſion hath failed,</hi> which hath been the cauſe people have periſhed, even becauſe of ignorance: Therefore come to Chriſt the light, the wiſdome of God, that you may learn only of him, and receive wiſdome of him, who maketh all them truly wiſe unto Salvation who come unto him and hear him, ſo then their ſouls come to live, and not before. And take not this as an idle tale or ſtory, for though my meſſage is not adorned with inticing words of mans wiſdome, or as mans wiſdome teacheth, yet know aſſuredly, that if ye reject it, it will be your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and you will be left without excuſe; as I ſaid, <hi>If God ſpared not the natural branches</hi> (when they ſinned) even they who were once truly grafted into the true Olive Tree, ſurely he will not ſpare you, who were never yet grafted into any thing but ſin and corruption, as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by your fruits of lightneſs, vanity, and vain glory, and the deportment both of you and your women, who goe in plaited haire, and in gold and ſilver, which was never the ornament of the holy women of God, nor of <hi>Sarah,</hi> but their ornament was that of the heart, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is with the Lord of great price, and is only accepted of God; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53099:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> your own habit is nothing differing from all the vain and abominable in your Nation, which the true Chriſtians were not to do, nor faſhion themſelves according to the former time of ignorance, but were to be renewed in their minds, and to be carefull in all things, and to walk an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable according to the holy calling wherewith Chriſt Jeſus had called them, who had left them a pure example, that they ſhould follow his ſteps. And ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am of Chriſt:</hi> But how ye do thoſe things, let the pure, juſt principle of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt judge in all your conſciences: Were you truly what you profeſſe your ſelves to be in words, would ye not be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt all the vanities and wickedneſs of the Nation, and bear your witneſs for God againſt it all? and ſo would be a ſweet ſavour unto the Lord in your generation, even as lights which are ſet on a hill: But inſtead of this ye are one with them in all manner of evill whatſoever, onely you differ in ſome external things in your worſhip, ſeeming to cry againſt Idolatry, and covetouſneſſe is in your hearts, which is as great Idolatry as can be named; and if you ſhould ſpeak againſt reſpecting of perſons, you are as much in it as they, and as partial in all your wayes, and any other abomination which is committed in the land, may be as commonly ſeen and heard amongſt you, as amongſt any other people in the Nation, as ſwearing, lying, vain talk, and fooliſh jeſting, whoring, &amp; whatſoever that may be named, pride, and vain cuſtome, and the like, and for a cover for all this, you ſay you are ſaved by grace; for ſhame, ſhame, ſhame, cover your faces, Are any ſaved by grace who are taught by it to deny all <hi>ungodlineſſe and worldly lust, and to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent evil world,</hi> and doth not? who live in wickeedneſs, and turn the Grace of God into wantonneſs, or rather turn from it; hath not the free grace of God appeared unto all unto Salvation, as well as unto you? as if a bear talk of being ſaved by grace would ſerve turn; why may not all be ſaved as well as you, ſeeing your fruit differeth nothing in ſubſtance? and then you ſay you are ſaved by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, but vaine
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53099:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> men ſhew your faith by your works, for if it be the living Faith, which gives victory over ſin, the other may alſo be brought into it by good works, which are the effects of the only true and living Faith, and ſo be converted unto it and be ſaved; but your profeſſion without a poſſeſſion doth but adde the more unto your condemnation, as you ſhall witneſs except ye repent; for if only a ſaying you believe in Chriſt Jeſus will ſave you, why may not thoſe you eſteem different from you, be ſaved as well as you, ſeeing they will in the particular ſay it, and affirm it as well as you, and both your fruits (in reſpect of life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) varie nothing at all. Read and conſider theſe things ſeriouſly, and repent, knowing that as the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirit is dead, ſo is Faith without works alſo dead.</p>
            <p>Again I ſay in love &amp; pity to your immortal ſouls, prize, prize Gods eternal love which is freely tendred unto you all, leaſt you cry when it is too late, Oh how have I ſlighted the day of my viſitation? and it be ſaid of you as it was of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>Oh Iſrael thou hast deſtroyed thy ſelf;</hi> for it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſins of a people or Nation which ſeparateth them from God, and brings judgements upon them or any Land, that the inhabitants may learn righteouſneſs; but if they refuſe to be warned thereby, and harden their necks, then will the Lord ſweep them away with the Boſome of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Therefore lay it to heart, for the ſins of this land hath ſurpaſſed the ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> who were made examples of Gods juſt judgements, that others might take warning.</p>
            <p>Therefore my bowels is truly moved in me towards you, that you may not ſlight the day of your viſitation, but diligently hearken to the Lord, which if you do, he will ſoon ſubdue all your enemies for you, and make you to ſhine (as his own elect and choſen people) as the Stars in the Firmament, and many ſhall deſire to be joyned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; yea the day haſtneth apace, <hi>That ten ſhall lay hold of h m which is a Jew, and ſay we will eat our own bread, and drink our own drink, only let us be called by thy name;</hi> yea, this and much more, which is hard to be uttered either by tongue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53099:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> or Pen, ſhall be the portion of him who is of the true cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, which is made without hands, who worſhips God in the Spirit, a City and habitation is prepared for them, <hi>whoſe builder and maker is God, wherein the Lamb ſhall be their Light, and they ſhall walk in it for ever and ever.</hi> Therefore come all away to the light, which is the true door into the new and Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> wherein no unclean thing can or ever ſhall enter thereby; by the light muſt ye come to be cleanſed, which is the blood of the Covenant, which is freely ſhed abroad for the cleanſing of all the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore trample it not under your feet, as the blood of a dead man, and count it not an unholy thing, for by it alone were all the Saints of old cleanſed, and it did not ſerve them onely to talk of, but were truly purged, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and made clean by it, and ſo witneſſed Juſtification and Sanctification in this life, without which they never could; for except you come to witneſſe your ſouls clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from ſin, and ſanctified with the blood of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant, you cannot be juſtified by God, for God juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth no unclean thing, and remember it is written, <hi>That without holineſſe, no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> and lay it to heart, and there ponder theſe things in the coole of the day, which if you do, <hi>The grace of God will not be beſtowed upon you in vain,</hi> but through its pure teachings and vertue you will come to witneſſe ſalvation to your ſouls, and death ſwallowed up in victory, and he that hath the power of it, which is the Devil; then will that ſaying be brought to paſs, <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> and will thank God with your ſouls, bodies, and ſpirits, and ſerve him therewith, as holy veſſels ſanctified to his uſe, who hath given you the victory over all; and living praiſe will iſſue out of your mouths, not by conſtraint, but willingly out of a pure heart for evermore, to the living praiſe of him, who hath redeemed your ſouls out of the horrible pit, and ſet your feet upon a Rock, even upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> to live and Reign for ever: And this is the true Salvation of God through Chriſt Jeſus, which thouſands witneſſe at this day in <hi>England,</hi> and praiſe the Lord with one heart,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53099:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> mind and ſoul continually, which is their only joy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, God only being witneſſed to be their Judge, King, and Law-giver, who hath ſaved them with everlaſting Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſin and uncleanneſs, <hi>and are tranſlated into the Kingdom of his dear Son,</hi> and there live and delight only to walk to the praiſe and glory of the glorious God of all grace, who hath thus beſtowed his rich grace and mercy upon them; which alſo is freely and richly tendred unto you, O ye inhabitants of <hi>France,</hi> therefore ſlight it not, but draw nigh unto God, and he will draw unto you, for he is a God at hand (and not afar off) even unto them who call upon him with a ſimple heart, and is a ready help unto ſuch in time of need; and you will witneſſe him ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you if ye embrace the riches of his grace, mercy and goodneſſe, which is freely tendred to every individual of you without reſpect of perſons; <hi>Therefore call upon the Lord while he is neere, leaſt when you call he will not anſwer,</hi> which is counſell of life unto you all, which if you reject, then hear what the Spirit ſaith, ye ſhall have your portions with the wicked, ſtiff-necked, unbelievers, and rebellious, and your children ſhall enjoy the bleſſing, for God of a truth will be glorified in many of them, and you alſo, if ye count not your ſelves unworthy of Eternal life, which is richly, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully tendred unto you. Therefore ceaſe from all your I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol-ſhepherds and hireling-Prieſts, which feed themſelves and not the flock, preach up ſin as long as men live, which ſhews they are imperfect Miniſters, and cannot make the comers thereunto perfect; therefore I ſay ceaſe from them in time, leaſt while the blind lead the blind ye both fall into the ditch, for they are truly the Miniſters of Satan, and preach up his power to be greater than the power of God, even to have more force to keep people in ſin, then the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God hath to redeem from ſin, (as hath already been ſaid,) and ſo make the coming of Chriſt to be of no effect, which was to redeem people from the Law (which was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion) up to God to live in his power, which was before tranſgreſſion was; therefore (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in what the Law could not doe, in that it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53099:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> was weak, God ſending his own Son in the likeneſſe of ſinful fleſh, to condemn ſin in the fleſh, that the righteouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh but after the Spirit:</hi> Mark, this was the true end of Chriſts coming, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Law, becauſe the Law is righteous, and layeth hold on the tranſgreſſor; but he came to deſtroy the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and ſo he redeems all who come unto him, from the curſe of the Law, by deſtroying the works of the Devil in people, that ſo the righteouſneſſe thereof might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in them by the power of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo they come to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent being bruiſed and wholly deſtroyed in them by Chriſt the ſeed of God, <hi>in whom all the promiſes are Yea, and Amen;</hi> and they who witneſſe this witneſſe the end of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the new birth which is incorruptible of God, which ſinneth not, and they who come to witneſſe this, know that the power of Satan is not greater then the power of God in Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaves his people from their ſins; and this is the only true living Miniſtry, which is to the ſalvation of the ſoul, and all who preach any other doctrine then this, (though we our ſelvs or an Angell from heaven) let them be accurſed; therefore conſider your doctrine who preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt perfection, and for keeping men in ſin as long as they live, and then the Devil knows he hath them ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough afterwards, <hi>for the wages of ſin is death,</hi> out of which there is no redemption if the creature dye therein, <hi>for as the tree falls ſo it lyeth:</hi> And this is the truth of God to all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth; therefore high and low, rich and poor, bond and free, be ye warned, and while ye have time prize it; and if ye call upon God (who without reſpect of perſons judgeth according to every mans work) <hi>paſſe the time of your ſojourning here in feare,</hi> and <hi>redeem the time for the days are evil,</hi> and <hi>work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> which if ye doe ye ſhall be everlaſtingly bleſſed in the end, which is the word of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth unto you all: Therefore while you have time prize it; this word doth the Lord often put into my heart unto you; for the dreadful day of his fierce unreſiſtable wrath is nigh at
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53099:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> hand, in which he wil deſtroy all workers of iniquity from off the earth, root and branch for ever, and to that man will he look, who is of a humble and contrite heart, &amp; trembleth at his word, and only ſuch ſhall obtain favour of him in that his dreadful day, and controverſie with all Nations; therefore is he ſending, and hath ſent his dear and precious Lambs and Servants forth to warn them, that they may repent and find mercy, leaſt his vengeance overtake them, and that they may be leſt without excuſe; and for this cauſe is this warning ſent unto you, O ye <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in <hi>France,</hi> that ye may alſo be warned to fly the wrath which is even at the door, for your meaſure of iniquity is even full, and haſtneth apace the finiſhing: Therefore be awakened and warned, that ye may find favour with him, who will not judge according to your perſons, but in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement will he judge you, even from the King that ſitteth upon the Throne, unto the ſlave that grindeth at the mill, and neither money nor favour ſhall be able to deliver any; therefore that ye may repent and find mercy is the true and faithfull deſire of my ſoul to the Lord for you my Countrey-men, whom the Lord hath warned to warn you, and hath ſhewed me (his ſilly worm) the evil and the good which ſhall ſurely come upon you; who in love and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God and your Souls hath not concealed it from you (whether you doe embrace, or reject his love and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, which is freely tendred unto you) that ſo in the day of account, with my Maker I may be found clear of your blood, and the blood of all men, which if I had, it would be too heavy for me to bear, for the Lord would require it at my hands, who hath called me from a far countrey, where I was an inhabitant about fourteen yeares, untill this work was laid on me, to viſit you <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in, and about <hi>Paris;</hi> but ye rejected me and deſpiſed me, and would not permit me to declare my meſſage of love unto you, which was from the Lord, and not my own, in teſtimony of which I was ready to ſeal it with my blood; but ſeeing ye would not receive it from the Lord, who called me from the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America</hi> to miniſter and ſerve the <hi>Indians</hi> elſwhere in his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53099:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> truth and goſpel, I ſhall be clear of your blood for ever; and at my return from <hi>Paris,</hi> the Lord laid it upon me to write this teſtimony unto you, before he would ſuffer me to go out of your Nation, and happy will ye be if ye receive it, but if ye wilfully reject it (as ye did me, and contemned my perſon) then wo will come upon you from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth for evermore: Therefore Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men, I beſeech you in the bowels of endleſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned love for ever, in, and with the ſame the Lord hath loved me, to lay it to heart, for my God is a conſuming fire, who will not in any wiſe condemn the innocent, nor acquit the guilty, for with him alone dwelleth equity and juſtice, which is the habitation of his Throne for ever, which you ſhall be made partakers of, who turn to him, and peace ſhall never depart out of your habitation. Let this thing be conſidered by all who love their ſouls, for what will it avail you to win the whole world, and loſe your own ſouls? is there any thing below the Sun but what is vanity and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit, and muſt come to an end? nay, verily there is not; therefore ſpend not your precious time any longer in taking care what you ſhall eat, or what you ſhall drink, or what you ſhall put on, for all theſe things ſuch ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter who know not God; but <hi>cast your care upon God, who will care for you,</hi> if ye come to walk, and live in his holy fear, and ſeek not honor one of another, but only that honour which comes from him, ſo will ye honour him, and he will make you truly honourable in the midſt of a rebellious and ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked people; and ſeek not to lay up treaſures on earth, but <hi>firſt ſeek ye the Kingdome of Heaven, and all things which are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for you ſhall be added unto you,</hi> for if the Lord taketh care for the birds of the aire, how much more will he take care for thoſe who put their truſt and confidence in him? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpend not your time in chambering and wantonneſſe, <hi>neither make proviſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts thereof,</hi> for the luſt warreth againſt the ſoul; but <hi>be ye ſober and watch, for the day of the Lord will come upon you as a thief in the night,</hi> and he will call you to an account of your ſtewardſhip, and how you have ſpent his money, for every one hath a manifeſtation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53099:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the ſpirit given him to profit withall, which he muſt give an account to his Lord of, for that's the talent, and wo be to him that hath not been faithful to improve it, <hi>but the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent hand maketh rich, and he which hath been faithful to a little ſhall be made ruler over much;</hi> ſo conſider ſeriouſly how you ſpend your time, and whoſe money you are improving, and to what uſe you put it to, for accordingly ſhall your reward be: Therefore Friends, as in the ſight of the living God in whom I live, and ſerve with my Spirit, I am very plain with you, recommending my ſelf to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God, that I have not hid the counſel of God from you, ſo far as he hath made it manifeſt to me concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you, neither have I gone to heal your hurt deceitfully, nor ſowed pillars under your arm-holes, nor daubed you with untempered morter, as the falſe prophets do, crying peace, peace to the wicked; but as the Lord hath ſhewed me the ſword of his wrath, which is ready to be ſheathed in the bowels of the wicked, I have in faithfulneſſe warned you of it, that ye might eſcape it, by turning from the evil of your wayes, for by no other way or meanes can you poſſibly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape it; therefore let not me be counted your enemy for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you the truth, knowing that the reproof of a friend is better than the kiſſe of an enemy, and an open reproof is better than ſecret love; therefore ſaith <hi>David, Let the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſmite me, and it ſhall be as an ointment upon my head,</hi> and you will alſo witneſſe it ſo upon yours, if ye come and ſubmit unto <hi>Davids</hi> humble ſpirit of prayer and repentance, which was the cauſe God did ſo delight in him above many, for the humble and contrite ſpirit (which <hi>David</hi> was of) God will in no wiſe deſpiſe, for he even confeſſed his ſin and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook it, and willingly ſubmitted unto the judgements of the Moſt High for it, by which meanes he had acceptance with God, <hi>And thy word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have hid in my heart, that I may not ſin againſt thee;</hi> for that is the dayly care of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart, leaſt God ſhould take his holy ſpirit from him, for he prayeth continually that God would renew his dayly countenance upon him, which made <hi>Davids</hi> heart more glad than thoſe who had all the encreaſe of the earth;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53099:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo all you who take <hi>Davids</hi> words to ſing and talk of, deal faithfully with your own ſouls, and ſee whether you are come to his ſpirit, yea, or nay, and until then his word and penitent heart is your condemnation, which you ſhall eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally witneſſe to be true in the day that by <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit ye ſhall be judged, who ſaid, <hi>depart from me all ye that do wickedly;</hi> and was made the ſong of the drunkard.</p>
            <p>Truly Friends, the Lord hath made my bowels as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fountain towards you, that you may no longer be of that generation which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, who are pure in their own eyes, and yet are not purged from their iniquity: I ſhall as being truly moved of the Lord thereunto, lay theſe following things before you to conſider ſeriouſly of, as being things which every one who dare profeſſe the name of Chriſt and Chriſtianity, ought truly to mind, to the end they may not be only Chriſtians in name but in nature, which will only ſtand you inſtead in the dreadful day of judgement, wherein God will appear with flames of fire, to render vengeance to the wicked, which day haſtneth apace.</p>
            <p>Therefore read and conſider, Whether Chriſt Jeſus, when he ſpake unto his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect,</hi> did not ſpeak really as he meant? And whether he would bid them be that which was impoſſible for them to be?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Read through the whole Scripture, and ſee if you can read of any other Salvation but that which is from ſin; And whether or no, that was not the promiſe of God unto <hi>Adam</hi> after he had ſinned, to wit, that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head, which ſeed was Chriſt? And whether this is not to be witneſſed in every regenerate man, or woman, yea, or nay? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Serpent be not head in all untill this be witneſſed, yea, or nay? For ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>we are ſaved by faith in Chriſt,</hi> whether is there any true faith which ſaves, but that which gives true and perfect dominion over all ſin? And whether there be any other true faith which juſtifieth before God? And whether this faith only be not the true faith of Gods Elect, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>God juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53099:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> not the ungodly,</hi> ſhewing that no unclean thing is juſtified before God? And can any in truth ſay that they are juſtified, but thoſe who witneſſe this faith, by which the juſt liveth and obtaineth victory, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether the free grace of God hath not appeared unto all men? And whether all thoſe who receive it, and are taught by it, are not led and taught to deny all ungodly luſts? And whether they who are not thus taught by it, are not of thoſe who turn it into wantonneſſe? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will not be their eternall condemnation, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether Chriſt according to <hi>Johns</hi> true and faithful teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which he bare of him, hath not enlightned every man which cometh into the world? And whether this Light doth not judge righteouſly for God, againſt all ſin in the conſciences of all men? And whether if they reject its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, it will not be their condemnation, yea, or nay? And whether God hath not ſo promiſed, that he would give Chriſt his only ſon for a Covenant of Light, that he might be his ſalvation even to the ends of the Earth? And whether any ever came to witneſſe ſalvation, but thoſe that thus witneſſed Chriſt a Covenant of Light to be their leader and teacher, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether God hath not promiſed that in his new and everlaſting Covenant all his people ſhall be taught of him? And whether thoſe who are yet looking at man for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be not out of this pure holy Covenant, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether God hath not promiſed that he will live and walk in his people? And whether they who do not witneſſe it, even their bodies to be the Temples of God, be not the Temples of the Devil, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether any are, or can truly be ſaid to be the ſons of God, but thoſe who are led by the Spirit of God? And whether any are true Chriſtians, but thoſe who have put on Chriſt, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether any are Chriſts, but thoſe who have the Spirit of Chriſt? And whether any can witneſſe the true Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but ſuch who have received the Spirit, yea, or nay?</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:53099:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Whether there be any other Baptiſme needful unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation but this, to wit, by one Spirit into one body, by the Holy Ghoſt, and by fire? And whether all other ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings are nothing but traditions of men, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether the true Chriſtians did not come to witneſſe Chriſt in this life to be wiſdome, juſtification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether Chriſt in the Saints was not the onely hope of their glory, even to live in them as he did in God, and through which they came to have fellowſhip with the Father? And whether they who came to witneſſe this were not ſanctified throughout in body, ſoul, and ſpirit, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether Chriſt did not give himſelf for his Church, that he might purge and ſanctifie it, and preſent it to the Father without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any can come to be true members of this Church, but thoſe who come to witneſſe a true purging in this life, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>the Church is in God,</hi> to whom no unclean thing can be united? And whether all who ſay they are members of the Church of Chriſt, and doe not witneſſe this, to wit, a cleanſing, be not lyars, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether the true Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus do not preach freely, as they have received freely? And whether they who preach for hire, gifts and rewards, or yearly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, are not Miniſters of Satan, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether any can be truly ſaid to be the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, but who are ſent by him, and called immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by his voyce unto his work? And whether all others are not of man, and by the will of man, who run and are not ſent, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether ſuch men who ſay they can never be freed, nor put off the body of ſin as long as they live, be not Miniſters of Satan? And whether they in effect do not prefer the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Satan to be greater to keep people in ſin, than the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt is to redeem and ſet at liberty from ſin, yea, or nay?</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:53099:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Whether the Croſs of Chriſt be not the power of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation to every one who believes, through which all who live in it come to be crucified to the world, and the world to them? And whether any be true Diſciples of of Chriſt, but thoſe who witneſſe it, and bear it dayly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with them, and follow Chriſt, taking him for their perfect example in all things, yea, or nay? Whether do not they who are true Miniſters of Chriſt, turn people from darkneſſe to light, and from Satans power to God? And whether are not they who are ſo turned come to witneſſe that which was before Satans power was, or ſin either, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether doth not all true Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus bring people off from mans teaching and wiſdom, unto Chriſt the wiſdome of God and his teaching? And whether he doth not bring them to the Anointing in them, which is the gift of God, ſo that they need not mans teaching, yea, or nay? And whether all they are not Miniſters of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan who Preach and teach otherwiſe; <hi>whoſe eyes are full of Adultery, and cannot ceaſe from ſin; while they promiſe to others liberty, they themſelves are not ſervants unto corruption,</hi> yea, or nay? And whether they be not ſuch of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, teaching things they ought not for filthy lucre ſake,</hi> who have not the word they ſpeak from the Lord, but ſeek it every one of his neighbour, and againſt whom the Lord is, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Theſe things being truly of abſolute concernment, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one who ſincerely deſireth ſalvation to their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſouls, to know and be rightly informed therein; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I propound them unto you, to be anſwered by the heads and wiſe amongſt you, who ſeem to be pillars to the reſt, that thereby your Prieſts and Teachers may manifeſt themſelves, whether they are true Miniſters of Chriſt, yea, or nay? which will appear by their anſwer, if they are the ſpiritual weaponed men, <hi>Who wreſtle not with fleſh and blood, but with principalities, and ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places, which captivates the creature, and keeps him in bondage and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:53099:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> for to no other end are theſe propounded unto them, but that truth may appear, and the ſimple come to be inſtructed, and that they may come to be redeemed from the power of their adverſary the Devil, <hi>Who goeth about like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devoure,</hi> and that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and truth may be ſet up amongſt the ſons of men, for God of a truth will be known to be greater in power to deliver his creature from ſin, then the Devil is to keep them in ſin; and this work hath the Lord already begun in the earth, and will haſten to finiſh it for his own glory ſake; for the glory of his renown ſhall go over all, and his name ſhall be dreadfull among the heathen, and greatly feared and honoured of all them who put their truſt in him, who are and ſhall be the onely bleſſed for evermore: But the wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God. Therefore, O ye <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> to whom theſe things are ſent, I charge you all in the power and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the living God (who hath created the Heavens and the earth, &amp; as you ſhall anſwer it in the dreadful day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) not to ſlight theſe things, but receive them as they are given forth to you; and if your Prieſts ſhall withſtand it, let them anſwer thoſe plain demands which are propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it, that ſo Gods eternal truth may ſtand over all for ever; and let their anſwer be ſent to any of the people of the Lord called <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> And they your Teachers who ſay they have the charge of your ſouls, and receive wages of you under that pretence, I ſhall yet adde this Query unto them for to anſwer: What the ſoul of man is? And as you prize the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſouls, mind theſe things, and ceaſe from man in time, <hi>whoſe breath is in his noſtrills, for whereof is he to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted?</hi> and come all to God alone for teaching, who hath promiſed to teach his people himſelf, which is his true living and everlaſting Covenant with his people for ever, which the people in <hi>England</hi> called <hi>Quakers</hi> do witneſſe; glory and immortal praiſe be unto him for ever, who hath manifeſted his name, power and glory amongſt them as in the days of old, by which he hath ſtruck dread unto their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53099:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> enemies, and ſet them as a Signet on the Crown of his head, and hath put a new Song in their mouths, even the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of the Lamb; for he hath manifeſtly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown their enemies in their ſight, and will do the like for you, (O ye <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and inhabitants of this Nation) if ye hear and obey his voice in this the day of his Almighty power; which if ye do, happy, happy, happy will ye be, and your poſterity for evermore; but if ye refuſe, then curſed, curſed, curſed will ye be from his holy pure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for evermore; which is his eternal word unto you all; and thus far I ſhall be clear of your blood if ye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: Remember <hi>Korah, Dathan, and Abiram,</hi> who periſhed in their gain-ſaying; and in love and bowels of pity, I ſay be ye warned betimes.</p>
            <p>Truly friends, I was a man as ye are, ſubject unto all manner of vanity which was under the Sun, paſſing my time in Singing and Muſick, fooliſh talking, and idle jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo was a captive to ſin and Satan, untill the Lord out of the boundleſſe riches of grace and mercy towards me, and many more in thoſe remote parts of the earth where I dwelt (who had as large a talk of Chriſt and what he did and ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſixteen hundred years ſince, as any people as ever yet I came nigh, and could talk of Faith in Chriſt, and being ſaved by grace and the like, while his pure grace was turned from by us, and we in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and the grace of God which was freely beſtowed upon us was our condemnation; and in this loſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done ſtate the Lord) ſent one of his meſſengers, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the way and path of holineſſe unto us, whoſe meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was light, and that Chriſt Jeſus had enlightned every one of us with his true light, which condemned us for ſin and evil in our conſciences from our youth up, and if we heeded this light it would lead us up to God, and we ſhould know him alone to be our teacher: This was the meſſage of glad tidings unto us, and their feet were beautifull upon the mountains who brought it, and I may truly ſay, bleſſed be the day of their going out with the meſſage of peace in their mouth for ever, for the witneſſe of God in me anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53099:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereto, and that their meſſage was true and faithfull, for I had that in me which had never conſented to the evil of my wayes from my youth up untill that day, but was a witneſſe againſt me when I did ſin againſt God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had brought ſorrow upon me, for my vaine and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed converſation; and after I had believed their report con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the holy pure light of Chriſt (as they told me it came from him and would lead to him) I witneſſed their words to be true, and at this time am ready to ſeale to the truth thereof with my blood, if called thereunto of the Lord; for through it I came to have acceſſe to God, and no other way, yet ſo as through judgement which laid hold of the tranſgreſſor in me, and all that ever I had done came to be judged by him who ſitteth upon the throne and liveth for evermore: So I came to witneſſe the promiſe of God in me, that judgement ſhould reſt for a light to the people, for it was ſo in me, and I heard a voice ſaying, <hi>This is the way, walk in it, turn neither to the right hand, nor to the left;</hi> ſo my teacher came to be near me, even in me, and will never be removed <hi>into a corner any more,</hi> if diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heeded and followed, which teacher is the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, which ſhined in the darkneſſe in me, though the darkneſſe could not comprehend it, but as I came to heed it diligently, it did comprehend all the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in me, and for me, and hath given me a clear diſcovery of all things pertaining to the Myſterie of the Kingdom of God, which are needful unto ſalvation; and I came to ſee <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt overturned which kept the ſeed of God in bondage in me, and I paſſed the Red Sea into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, where I came to know a ſacrifice offered up, which he did accept, and not before; and then I came to mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to the giving forth of the Law, which was terrible to the fleſh, but it was, and is glorious unto me, and will be for ever, for it laid hold on nothing but on that part which is eſtranged from God, wherein I had ſeen many wonders, and overturning of enemies, yet many temptations and provocations I had to returne into <hi>Egypt</hi> again, and that I ſhould never be able to enter the promiſed Land, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53099:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> were ſo great, which I know all will come to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in like manner who come truly to travail towards the Land of reſt; but to ſuch an one I ſay, be of good cheer and courage, for if thy heart be given to God, he will of a truth be with thee in all thy travails, even to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and thy work will be only to keep in the Faith, and ſo thou wilt find thy ſtrength will be to <hi>ſtand ſtill and ſee the Salvation of God:</hi> For this teſtimony I faithfully give and bear for the Lord, that it is he only who doth and will ſubdue all their enemies in and for them (be they never ſo many or mighty) who truly put their whole truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his name alone; <hi>who is a ſtrong tower in time of need;</hi> I ſay ſuch ſhall poſſeſs the gates of their enemies, and ſhall come to witneſs with me, as I do at this day, <hi>the elder to ſerve the younger,</hi> which is the true work and promiſe of God, and the true travail of the ſeed into the Lord of reſt, and there is no other ſalvation to be looked for, even the ſubduing &amp; caſting out of the ſeed of the bond woman, that the Seed of the free woman (which is <hi>Christ the Son of the moſt high God, over all bleſſed for evermore,</hi>) may have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminency in the creature; and thus coming out of <hi>Egypts</hi> darkneſſe, I came to ſee that all the teachers in the world made by the will of man, were but ſoul-deceivers, for they had not the word from the Lord, neither were they ſent by him, therefore did not they profit the people at all, and were but <hi>Babels</hi> builders, one building and another deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all in the confuſion, and the moſt refined of them were but Miniſters of the letter, and not of the Spirit, boaſting of other mens lines made ready unto their hands, ſerving and worſhipping the works of their own hands, <hi>according to the oldneſſe of the letter, and not according to the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Spirit, and teaching them for Doctrine the traditions of men:</hi> And thus are poor people in an expectation of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and ſalvation through their teachings, but all in vain, for when they have heard them all their life time, they tell them they can never be freed from ſin, and yet tell them they are good Chriſtians, though they be Drunkards, Swearers, Liars, and wicked perſons; and this is the fruits
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53099:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> of their Miniſtry, which all ſhall witneſs with me, who come to the one teacher and Shepherd of the ſoul, who ſaveth all to the uttermoſt that come unto him, who <hi>is the light of the world, and enlightneth every one which cometh into the world,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, who is the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> and he is the door, even the light, for the way is but one, the truth is but one, which is the light the onely way to God, and there is not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>And no man cometh to the Father but by me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt the light, the door, the way, the life, ſo none can ever come to God, nor the way to God, nor the truth, but who comes to the light, wherewith they are inlightned, which comes from Chriſt, and condemneth all the evil that is in the creature, and ſheweth a man all that ever he hath done; for ſaith the woman of <hi>Samaria, Is not this the Christ who hath told me all that ever I have done?</hi> So all likewiſe who come unto the light they witneſſe with her, and with me, the ſame thing; and all who come into ſubjection unto it, ſhall come to witneſſe the wild Colt tamed upon which never man ſat, and then and not till then is <hi>Hoſannah</hi> ſung, nor bleſſed can he ever be <hi>who comes in the name of the Lord</hi> by any, untill this be fulfilled and witneſſed by them and in them; and this onely is the ſtate of a true convert, and true Chriſtian, and is my teſtimony for the Lord, which ſhall ſtand for ever, whether ye will hear, or forbear: And thus far have I cleared my conſcience towards you, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towards God, and love to your immortal ſouls; therefore prize it while ye have time, leaſt the things which <hi>belong to your peace, be hid from your eyes,</hi> and a lamentation be taken up by the juſt for you, as was over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaying, <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, how often would I have gathered thee, as a Hen gathereth her chickins under her wings, and thou wouldeſt not?</hi> Therefore I ſay again, and again, lay it to heart, and prize Gods everlaſting love unto you all which is freely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unto you, notwithſtanding that your ſins have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the meaſure of many Nations; and remember <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh who repented</hi> (at <hi>Jonahs</hi> preaching) <hi>in Sackcloath and aſhes,</hi> whoſe ſins and abominations never ſurpaſſed yours, which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53099:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> is a word of truth unto you all; therefore take her for an example and repent in time, leaſt Gods judgements over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you, for Gods anger is kindled againſt the workers of iniquity, he will deſtroy them from off the face of the earth, that nothing but holineſs may reign for evermore, <hi>And the meek alone ſhall inherit the earth for ever and ever.</hi> And this is the infallible Decree and purpoſe of my God, which can never be recalled, but will ſtand for ever, and it haſtneth to be fulfilled, and he will overthrow Powers, Princes, Kings and Dominions, even all ſuch as ſhall oppoſe, or withſtand him in this his glorious work, whom he will deſtroy in his fury, &amp; will break them in pieces: Therefore O ye pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the earth, down with your Crowns at the feet of the Lamb, and ye ſhall find mercy; but if ye reſiſt him, he will grind you to powder.</p>
            <p>And this is the word of the Lord God unto you all, and I ſhall be innocent before the Lord God of my life for ever; therefore be awakned, and beware what you do now ye are warned, for you will be left without excuſe if you periſh, and you ſhall know that you have been warned in time, by one whom the Lord hath truly required ſo to do, which if I ſhould not, wo, wo, would be unto me for ever; ſo I ſhall lay down my life here in Peace and Reſt, and ſhall rejoyce if ye take warning more then in the treaſures of <hi>Egypt;</hi> who am called by the name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Baily.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53099:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
